<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvarning-piece for the slumbring virgins. Or, An alarm to the friends of the bridegroom, in some awakening meditations upon Christ's own watch-word, Matth. 26.41. Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation, &amp;c. / By Geo: Scortreth, preacher of the Gospel in Lincoln.</title>
            <author>Scortreth, George, b. 1612 or 13.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 104 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94266</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1638_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209055</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867960</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867960</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94266)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 206:E1638[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvarning-piece for the slumbring virgins. Or, An alarm to the friends of the bridegroom, in some awakening meditations upon Christ's own watch-word, Matth. 26.41. Watch and pray, that ye enter not into temptation, &amp;c. / By Geo: Scortreth, preacher of the Gospel in Lincoln.</title>
                  <author>Scortreth, George, b. 1612 or 13.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 175, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Brewster, at the Three Bibles in Paul's Church-yard, near the west end,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XXVI, 41 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VVarning-Piece FOR THE Slumbring Virgins.</p>
            <p>OR, AN ALARM TO THE <hi>Friends of the Bridegroom,</hi> IN Some Awakening <hi>Meditations</hi> upon Chriſt's own Watch-word, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.41. <hi>Watch and Pray, that ye enter not into temptation,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Geo: Scortreth,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel in <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 16.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, I come as a thief, bleſſed is he that Watcheth, &amp; keepeth his garments, leſt he walk naked, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Brewſter,</hi> at the Three Bibles in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, near the Weſt End, 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:2"/>
            <head>To the Friends and followers of the Lamb.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in our Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Had not thought to have prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any of my poor Labours in the Lord; though i'has been much upon my heart, they might be imprinted upon the hearts of the hearers by the Spirit of the living God: But ſome late impulſes have been upon my ſpirit, (ſince infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties have grown upon me) to leave a few Words with the ſervants of Chriſt before I leave them; looking up to him, to leave his bleſsing with them; and that upon theſe and the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations: <hi>1.</hi> The ſtrange Slum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings of ſo many backſliding Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians at this day, have ſomewhat awakened my drowſie ſpirit; and my eye hath affected my heart, to ſee ſo many ſleepy eyes, and heavy hearts; ſo that I am not at reſt; till I have
<pb facs="tcp:170191:3"/>eaſed my own ſoul in warning them openly, as in weeping for them in ſecret. <hi>2.</hi> The Lord hath been fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing me with awakening diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; morning by morning awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ear to receive inſtruction: and while he hath ſhaken his rod of Fatherly Correction over me, a deep Conviction hath fallen from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon me, that it is the work of the day in its day, for the Watchmen to cry aloud, ſaying, <hi>Awake, Awake. 3.</hi> I have ſome ſweet perſwaſions through mercy, that whiles I am at the Lords work, ſtirring up others to watch and pray, I ſhall find him at work within, ſtirring me up to take hold of him; and giving in ſome awakening heart-reflexions upon theſe Meditations of Watchfulneſſe; and my heart tells me, the Watchmen of all others would be well awakened, and ever upon their Watch at ſuch a day as this. <hi>4.</hi> Pity to ſlumbring Saints, who hear not the ſounding
<pb facs="tcp:170191:3"/>of their own bowels to make them pity themſelves, hath moved me to knock at their doors, and ask them how they do at heart; They little think (alas) now their hearts are aſleep, of the ſorrowes, that are coming upon the men and women that are at eaſe in Zion, as ſorrow upon a woman in travell. <hi>5.</hi> The love of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains me to call upon his ſloathfull Servants to ariſe and fall to their Maſters work; who hath moſt to do i'th laſt dayes, and would not be left alone at it: many heads, hands and hearts buſie together, would make light work: 'twould go merrily on, and not ſo heavily, as now it does, whiles ſo many heads and hearts are heavy with ſleep. <hi>6.</hi> The ſtirring Appetites of ſome hungry craving ones, (indeared to me in the bonds of the Goſpel,) who are daily waiting with longing for one cluſter of grapes or other, from the Celeſtial <hi>Canaan,</hi> have made me the more willing to
<pb facs="tcp:170191:4"/>preſſe this one grape for their ſakes: happily they may find a little ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in it, (though none elſe ſhould) as taking and taſting it with a good will, from his hand, whoſe heart is towards them. And if any of theſe ſhould unhappily be overtaken with that dead ſleep of midnight-ſecurity, which hath ſurprized ſo many at this day; who knowes but the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of one that is their friend, may prevail with them, to riſe and open the door of their hearts, when the Bridegroom himſelf ſhall knock, who is their beſt and deareſt Friend i'th World.</p>
            <p>Theſe being the wheels which have ſet this Watch on motion, you may not expect any Eye or Ear-affecting curioſity, but heart-awakening Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel Simplicity; the entiſing words of mans wiſdome have lull'd many aſleep: and 'tmuſt be plainneſſe of ſpeech in the demonſtration of the Spirit, that muſt awaken them. I
<pb facs="tcp:170191:4"/>have moſt to do in this Work with Wiſdomes Children, who have learnt to become fooles, that they may be wiſe, and had rather hear one word ſpoken to the underſtanding, then a thouſand words in an unknown tongue.</p>
            <p>The corporal weakneſſes and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wants of one groaning under an heap of infirmities, will make a ſufficient Apology for all wants and weakneſſes as to matter or method: 'Tis broken meat, this, for broken hearts, who will be gathering up a few Crums here and there; and if it be well digeſted within, 'twill be the leſſe matter, though it be ſo indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted without.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible, 'tis ſowen in great weakneſſe, (alas, how can ſo poor a nothing Creature do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe?) yet I am not out of heart or hopes, through grace, but it may riſe up in power, to the raiſing up of ſome that are aſleep in ſin, and the row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:170191:5"/>up of others that are under a ſinful ſlumber, by the power of the Spirit: which is his hearts deſign and deſire, who would willingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak your heart-remembrances, while he takes the humble boldneſse to be one of your weak, (though willing) Remembrancers in the Name of the Lord, that he may be accounted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be found a Watchful Servant of Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithful Servant for Jeſus ſake, <hi>G. S.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in little Queenſtreet, Lond. M. <date>
                     <hi>7. 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:5"/>
            <head>To my welbeloved Friends, endeared to me in the love and bonds of the Goſpel, at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> or elſewhere.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing laid aſide by the hand of my righteous Father, as to the publique work of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry amongſt you; you have been much upon my heart, in my private Meditations, to ſtirre you up and put you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance to wait upon our Lord, and for him, who will meet thoſe with rejoycing,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5.</note> that remember him in his wayes. The openings of your hearts to me in much affection, and compaſſion, as many of your eyes witneſſed at our parting, (not knowing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſhould ſee the faces of one another any more) and as your affectionate remembrances
<pb facs="tcp:170191:6"/>of me, while abſent, and under preſent bodily preſſures, do ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently teſtifie, have much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoke my heart on your behalf to leave this Watch-word with you, if I ſhould now take my Reſt and ſleep in Jeſus. And if the Father of mercies ſhould graciouſly raiſe me up by his ſtrength, to ſpend and be ſpent amongſt you, 'twould be a ſweet mercy, to find you in a waiting, watching poſture: 'Twill be the more ſeaſonable to knock, where they are awakened, and to ſtrike while the iron's hot; The Word of Life will be moſt welcome to quickned ſpirits.</p>
            <p>That you may read theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing awakening Meditations with open eyes and hearts, let me preſent you with a few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratory hints, to an awakened poſture, happily your ſight may be a little cleared by this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte
<pb facs="tcp:170191:6"/>(as <hi>Jonathans</hi> was upon his taſting a little honey from the end of his rod) if you look up for eye-ſalve from Heaven, while you are looking on them.</p>
            <p>And firſt, by way of Counſel, 1. Hearken as with both Ears to the glad-tydings of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; you'l find, that good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports from Jeſus Chriſt, under Evangelical diſpenſations, will exceedingly affect, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally awaken your hearts. The ſweetneſs of the bunch of grapes upon that ſtaffe of beauty feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly taſted, will ſet you a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the choice fruits of the heavenly <hi>Canaan;</hi> and hungry ſouls will not eaſily ſleep over their ſpiritual food. 2. Walk up to light received in the love and power of it; you'l find it a good thing indeed to behold the pure heart-quickening beams of the Sun of Righteouſneſſe:
<pb facs="tcp:170191:7"/>It's Soul-taking too; 'Twill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low you, as you follow it; Then ſhall you know,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.3.</note> if you follow on to know the Lord; his goings forth will be prepared as the morning, ſhining upon you, and within you, and cauſing your path to ſhine more and more to the perfect day: And you will find this Sun-ſhine marvellouſly clearing and quickening the eyes of your underſtanding: 3. Knock oft at your own doors, you may be bold at home, and ask every day, How all does within; what ſtrength of faith; what warmth of love; what growth in grace, &amp;c. much Soul-ſearching, will very much prevent Soul-ſlumbring: Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muning with Conſcience will keep it awake, and it will cry loud in your ears to keep you awake. 4. Stir up one another, and that with importunity, to
<pb facs="tcp:170191:7"/>ſtir up the grace of Chriſt that is in you, to do good to all, &amp;c. and all the good you can; and to do what you find in your hands to do for God, with all your might, and that while you have opportunity;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10.</note> for there's no work i'th grave, whither we are going. 'Twill be one of the beſt deeds of pure charity at this day, to viſit crazy ſickly ſoules, that lie languiſhing and ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring under ſpiritual Conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in the Name of the Lord; and to propound heart-ſearching Queſtions to quicken them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of heart ſeparating Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, which have deaden'd them. And ſure it would be a very ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable work in this hour of temptation, amongſt Chriſtian friends, (at diſtance) to take up that Primitive practice of the bleſſed Servants and Martyrs of Jeſus, by quickening up one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>others
<pb facs="tcp:170191:8"/>ſpirits with heart-awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Letters. I cannot but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this labour of Love to ſuch as are preſent with one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in ſpirit and love, when abſent in body, as that which ſome in our dayes have found a ſweet bleſſing in, even as in that cluſter mentioned, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.8.5. Give all diligence in the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent and fervent performance of all Goſpel-duties with a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-ſpirit, ſetting grace on work in all by the ſupply of the Spirit; and if you find your hearts rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to follow the Lord fully in all the work he has cut up for you, you'l find work enough ready at your hands and hearts to keep you awake. 6. Caſt up your ſpiritual accounts every day, with an eye to that great Day, when every one muſt give an account of himſelf to the Judge of quick and dead; oft
<pb facs="tcp:170191:8"/>Soul-reckonings will rowſe up your ſpirits much, to wait for the Bridegroom with loyns girt, and lamps burning,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.6.</note> as if you heard the cry at midnight.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by way of <hi>Caution.</hi> 1. Take heed of an heavy Ear under the Sound of the Goſpel, leſt your ears ſhould tingle for it another day. The Seers eyes muſt needs weep in ſecret for you, if they behold you ſleeping openly under the Lords all-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye; 'Twill ſadden the hearts of weak Chriſtians to ſee you heavy-hearted under that Goſpel of grace, by which they and you have been often awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and carnal hearts will be the more apt to ſlight that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall food which they ſee you ſleep over. 2. Take heed of reſting in a form of godlineſſe, without power, of taking up with the letter, without the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
<pb facs="tcp:170191:9"/>or being contented with a Name to live, without that new Name, and a new heart and life: you may lie dead at the letter, till you die, but the Spirit will quicken you, and put life into your ſpirit; you may eaſily ſlumber under the form of an outward profeſſion, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant exerciſe of the power of godlineſſe will effectually awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken you. 3. Dally not with any beloved luſt, nor be dandled upon any <hi>Dalilahs</hi> lap, leaſt you fall aſleep upon't, and be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed; if your hearts go after any ſtrange lovers, you muſt needs loſe your firſt love, to your firſt husband, and be left heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and ſpiritleſſe; if you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge any right eye, or right hand, how dark will the right eye be? and how dead the right hand of your inward man? you muſt watch over your own ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb facs="tcp:170191:9"/>yea, over every ſin ſo, as ever you would be found watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at Gods Word, or chearful in his way. Senſuality in any kind will breed ſpiritual ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at firſt, and bring perplexity of ſpirit at laſt. Sin's calm muſt needs end in a ſad ſtorm. 4. Take heed of ſelf-ſeeking, and ſeeking great things to your ſelves. A ſelfiſh ſpirit will be ſluggiſh in ſpirituals; if you once begin to take your fill of creature-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, you'l have no ſtomack to the things of Chriſt, but even ſleep at his breaſt: The love of the world will eat out your love to God, his Word, his work, his people, &amp;c. If you be all upon't, riſing early to eat the bread of ſorrows,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.2.</note> you'l loſe that ſweet ſleep he gives his beloved, and be caſt into a falſe ſlumber, feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your ſelves with fooliſh fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſaying, <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170191:10"/>where little eaſe is to be found, when the heart is drunk with the ſtrong wine of the Worlds cup, or drown'd in the ſweet waters of its own Ciſtern, 'twill certainly fall into a dead ſleep; and Chriſtians overloaden with thick clay, we ſee with ſorrow, how heavily they drive. 5. Take heed of ſlighting any holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and of a ſlight frame of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in them. 'Tis a ſlighting of God himſelf, who will lightly eſteem ſuch, and leave them to their own ſlothful ſpirits. A ſluggiſh indiſpoſition will ever attend ſinfull omiſſions; and ſuch as dare be bold in the omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of good, are in danger to become baſe and vile in the committing of evill: if your hearts backſlide in ſecret from humble communion with God in his holy wayes, he will turn his back upon you, and leave you
<pb facs="tcp:170191:10"/>to eat the fruit of your own wayes; and then, alas, how weak will your hearts be, in, and to, any thing that's good? how wofully evill? 6. Take heed of grieving the good Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God; leſt he go away ſadly, and leàve you to the heavineſſe of your own ſpirits. Oh, if you quench the heavenly ſparks of his holy motions, the fire of your love and zeal will quickly be going out, and you'l grow cold at heart. Oh do not, do not tempt the Holy Ghoſt, no, not for a world, leſt he withdraw his light, life, power, and peace from you; and then how dark and dead, heartleſſe and helpleſſe, will you lie in this hour of Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:11"/>
            <p>Theſe are the broken thoughts of one of your poor heart-friends, when afflicted and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in body, yet affected, as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in ſpirit, with the ſenſe of the room he hath had in your hearts, while the hand of the Lord hath touched him; What in mercy he hath brought to my hand and heart, (while I had onely his own Book with mee) I leave to the bleſſing of his own hand, upon your hearts and mind.</p>
            <p>Now the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God, and the patient waiting for of Chriſt. And I beſeech you Brethren for his ſake, and the love of the Spirit, that you ſtrive together and aſunder in your prayers to God for me, that he would conſider my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and know my Soul in
<pb facs="tcp:170191:11"/>adverſity, that I may rejoyce in his mercy; and that I may come unto you with joy by the Will of God, and may with you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed, through the gracious preſence of Chriſt, to the praiſe of his grace, to whoſe bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, direction, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I humbly commit you, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your much obliged Friend and Servant in the Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>G. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_Christian_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:12"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:12"/>
            <head>Chriſtian Reader,</head>
            <p>AS 'tis the ſpecial Office of ſome men to be Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſo 'tis the common duty of all men to Watch. That ſome men are appointed to watch over others, cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe any mans neglect of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over Himſelf. All the Ports of the Body, the Eyes, the Ears, the Lips, (at which the Soul is continually iſſuing out by ſeveral acts, or taking in from ſeveral Objects) need a continual watch upon them; how much more doth that moſt important Piece of all, the Heart? We ſhould alwayes watch what God is doing, we ſhould watch what God is ſpeaking, what he ſpeaks to us in his Word, what he ſpeaks to us in his Works; We
<pb facs="tcp:170191:13"/>ſhould watch what he ſpeaks to move us unto prayer, and what he ſpeaks in anſwer to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which we have made in prayer. How watchfull ſhould they be, who have all theſe, and many more, occaſions of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? We read in <hi>Daniel,</hi> (Chap. 4. 13.) <hi>Of a Watcher and a Holy one that came down from heaven;</hi> And ſurely none on earth can be <hi>Holy Ones, unleſſe they be Watchers.</hi> The careleſſe Soul is alwayes a corrupt one; and Security layeth us open to all impurity. Satan watcheth to make us Halt, and evil men watch for our Haltings; we ſhall never take either eaven or clean ſteps, unleſſe we watch our own goings, and ponder the path of our feet: Watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe being ſo indiſpenſible a Duty, how glad ſhould we be
<pb facs="tcp:170191:13"/>of any thing either to awaken us, or keep us awake? The Learned and Godly Authour of this enſuing Diſcourſe hath <hi>beaten ſuch an Alarm, and ſhot off ſuch a Warning-Piece in our Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> that if the Virgins ſlumber ſtill, as their ſecurity will be inexcuſable, ſo their calamity will be unavoidable. What can they look for, who will not watch to pray, But that <hi>God</hi> (as he once did, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.28.) <hi>ſhould watch over them to pluck up, and to break down, and to deſtroy, and to afflict?</hi> What can they look for, who will not watch to do good, but that, <hi>God,</hi> (as another Prophet ſaith he once did, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.13.) <hi>ſhould watch upon the evill, and bring it upon them?</hi> They who will not take warning, deſerve to be made one. Having peruſed this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall of Watchfulneſſe, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb facs="tcp:170191:14"/>it into the hands and to the hearts of all thoſe, who would find peace, and be found in peace, when their Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth. It was ſad, that the Diſciples eyes were ſo heavy, that they could not watch with Chriſt one hour, when he was going out of the world. And it will be more ſad with thoſe, whoſe hearts are ſo heavy, that they cannot watch for the return of Chriſt at all houres: who therefore hath not told us, the particular hour of his coming, that we at all hours might be kept watching for it. And Bleſſed will thoſe Servants be, whom when their Lord cometh, he ſhall find watching and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or watching unto prayer, that they enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that they may be kept in the hour of temptation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:14"/>
            <p>Reader, That his Book may be bleſſed from above to make thee Watchfull, is his Prayer, who readily Approves it for the Preſſe, and publick Uſe of this Slumbring Age,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:15"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:15"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THey who keep cloſe to the Lord Chriſt in holineſſe of Life, and purity of Doctrine, are <hi>Virgins,</hi> whether particular Perſons, or Churches: Such being expos'd to many Temptations, and ſubject to much Slumbring, here is a <hi>Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Piece</hi> for them. The great Watchman of <hi>Iſrael</hi> warn'd his Apoſtles, yea all to Watch:<note place="margin">Mark 13.37.</note> ſo doth this good Watchman in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Watching is a Duty of grand im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. <hi>Noah, Lot, David, Peter,</hi> and other Worthies were tempted, ſlumbred, and ſuffered much for want of Watchfulneſſe. When Kings ſlumber, they may loſe a skirt of their garments;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.14.</note> and
<pb facs="tcp:170191:16"/>when <hi>Virgins</hi> ſlumber they may loſe their whole Garments, all their Ornaments,<note place="margin">Rev. 16 15.</note> and the ſhame of their nakedneſſe appear. The vigilant Author hath prepar'd and fitted this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> to prevent ſuch evils; Its little, but of much worth, being Judicious, Succinct, and Spirituall. Bulky Volume, muſt give place. It's full of Apples of gold in pictures oſ ſilver, choyce Truths in choice ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions. Reader, wouldſt thou be a wiſe, watchful, and experimental Chriſtian, look ſeriouſly into this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> lay the Contents of it cloſe to thy heart, and be ſure to have thy deſire.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Greenhill. Geo: Griffiths.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:16"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 9. line 3. read Spirit, for, ſpirits. p. 13. l. 1. r. heart-duty, for hearty-duty. p. 21. l. 8. r. her, for his. l. 12. about, for abou. p. 23. <hi>ult.</hi> work, for worth. p. 50. l. 3. r. work, for prophecy. p. 55. l. ult. they, for this. p. 65. l. 16. as, for at. p. 71. Gen. 28. for 18. p. 72. l. 4. fear, for hear. p. 79. l 7. you, for theſe. line 9. your, for their. p. 86 l. 12 fully, for full. p. 87 l. 13 It's, for <hi>Jobs.</hi> p. 93 l. 1. as, for us. line 9. God, for Gods. p. 115 <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. for 14. leaſt, for laſt. p. 138 line 1. tow, for bow. p. 142 l. 11. with, whoſe lips had, for, with thoſe lips that. p. 143 line ult. and you, for, and put. p. 145 line 4. reſt, for coaſt. p. 152. the better: could, for, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could. p. 153. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.34. for, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.23. p. 155. l. 8. Can you, for Yea can. p. 164 l. 15. multiformity, for multifariety. p. 165. l. 23. and by ſwallowing, for, ſwallowing. p. 172. l. 16. as this, as they waited, for, as thus waited.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170191:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170191:17"/>
            <head>A Warning-Piece FOR THE <hi>Slumbring Virgins.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 26.41.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Watch and Pray, that ye enter not into temptation.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN the 37th verſe of this Chapter, we find, Jeſus took <hi>Peter,</hi> and the two Sons of <hi>Zebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee, and began to be ſorrowfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 17.1.2.</note> &amp;c: They that had ſeen his glory in the Mount, when <hi>his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſhined as the Sun,</hi> &amp;c: muſt now ſee him under a Cloude, his glory vailed; they beheld him in his Triumph, and muſt ſee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170191:18"/>him in his trouble. 'Tis Chriſts familiar way to be before-hand with his ſuffering Servants, to give them ſome hearty draughts, of the Cup of conſolation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he put into their hands the Cup of <hi>trembling;</hi> And 'tis a ſweet heart-taking method, well-becoming our tender-hearted Phyſitian, who loves to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting his poore ones with ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercies, ſo preparing them for ſufferings for him, by declare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his lovelineſſe and love to them.</p>
            <p>In the 40th verſe:<note place="margin">Verſ. 38</note> Chriſt finds his Diſciples aſleep, when he had newly called upon them to watch (ſo apt are we to ſleep under awakning teachings) when he was heavie and ſorrowfull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the death, how heavie were their eyes? how heartleſſe they at ſuch a time, even as dead men? they cannot watch with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170191:18"/>him, or for him,<note place="margin">Verſ. 40.</note> when his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were watching to take him. Ah poore helpleſſe, Spirit-leſſe friends to him, who had ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended them; His own diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples have leaſt care to watch, when greateſt cauſe to watch; now was their time if ever to watch, when he ſo awakened, and now they let their watchfall What, not watch with me one houre? Is it come to this? no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Souldiers under ſo good a Captain? what, deale ſo ill with mee, who have dealt ſo well with you? Yea, not watch with me one houre, who have watched ſo long over you for good? And now the houre is come too? If not for mee, yet for your ſelves <hi>for when the Shepherd is ſmitten, the Sheep will be ſcattered;</hi> But no warning will keepe them awake when the heart's aſleepe; he comes once, and againe, yea
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170191:19"/>the third time and finds them ſleeping (thus the ſleepie evill growes upon us) we are uſually moſt ſecure, when leaſt ſafe, and heavieſt with ſleep, under hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vieſt awakning providences.</p>
            <p>In the Text, we have Chriſts faithfull watch-word, or friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alarme to his ſlumbring Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; where obſerve.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A double duty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</item>
               <item>2. A double reaſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. A double duty command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, watch and pray; an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent preſent remedie againſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſecurity; A word in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; an happie conjunction, a bleſſed paire, joyned together by Chriſt himſelf, let no man put them aſunder: watching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prayer will be helpleſſe; and prayer without watching will be heartleſſe; but both together,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170191:19"/>heartfull and helpfull; Prayer without watching will never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken us; and watching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prayer, will never awaken the Lord, to watch over us for good; but both togeather will bring in many awakening, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and comforting viſits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and our Souls: watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in prayer makes it a good watch, and prayer in watching makes all things work for good.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A double reaſon commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Leſt ye enter into temptation: The Spirit indeed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Ye are expoſed to temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</item>
               <item>2. Ye are indiſpoſed to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Yee are expoſed to temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, if you do not watch and pray, you tempt the Lord to lead you into temptation, and leave you there; you tempt the tempter to tempt you, if you do
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170191:20"/>not watch and pray, he'l watch to make a prey of you; And you tempt your ſelves, you lie neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to and faireſt for temptations, when you are fartheſt from watchfull ſupplication. 1. You cloſe with temptations, you are in the mid'ſt of them before you be aware; if you watch not to ſhut the doore againſt them, you open the doore to them, there will be temptations upon you within and without, and you will be within them; while you lie ſleepie and prayerleſſe upon a bed of eaſe, you even lay a Cuſhion for Satan to lie down by you; you enter into temptation, and temptations will enter into you. 2. Temptations will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe you, you'l not know how to get out, when once in; you are in danger to be loſt i'th croud; you may be eaſily enſnared, but not ſo eaſily enlarged; 'tis hard
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170191:20"/>getting out of the Devills laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ye are indiſpoſed to oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; the fleſh is weak, and your temptations ſtrong, here obſerve,
<list>
                  <item>1. Chriſts candid conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>2. His cleare conviction; <hi>the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His Conceſſion; <hi>the Spirit is willing;</hi> your heart is good, though your hand be ſhort; theres ſinceritie in you, though you want abilitie: Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not find in his heart to break the bruiſed reed, the broken heart; he owns their willingneſſe with a good will, though much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in them; 'tmay do one good at heart to ſee, how his heart was upon their hearts, when their heads were heavie; how ſweetly his Spirit ſympathizeth with their Spirits; 'tis like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170191:21"/>the Spirit is willing (ſaith he).</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Conviction; the <hi>fleſh is weak;</hi> Chriſt is willing to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlook their infirmities, but will have them look upon them; they muſt not indulge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; for his indulgencie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them; Here's Counſel im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, to take care of their Spirits, that they may be quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, cheriſhed, and ſtrengthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Spirit, who helps to will and do of his good pleaſure, that to will may be preſent with them and to perform too.</p>
            <p>And here's Caution intimated, to take heed to the fleſh, to keep them humble, and ſenſible of their weakneſſe, that he might perfect his ſtrength in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſumme up all under this one word, and 'tis Chriſts own; Watch, Oh
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170191:21"/>that he would own it, and follow it home to our hearts by his Spirits, that we may own it for his ſake.</p>
            <p>Obſ. <hi>'Tis an Evangelical Duty to Watch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is wiſdoms own Counſel, and muſt be her Childrens care; The Captain of our ſalvation, gives this word to his Souldiers, to awaken them to work out their ſalvation, &amp;c: Now Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers upon pain of death, muſt be at a word of command: The watchfull Shepherd of Souls calls upon his ſheep to watch, and his voyce they moſt heare; How oft is this hammer lift up, to knock at the everlaſting doors of our hearts, even by the King of glory himſelf? Ten times at the leaſt, we have this word ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the Evangeliſts, from Chriſts own Mouth: How apt are we to ſleep on both eares,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170191:22"/>that he muſt cry ſo hard, and call ſo oft upon us, ſaying, Watch, watch, watch, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> how hardly are we awakened; what a dead ſleep is upon us; that there muſt be ſuch crying, jogging, knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> How dangerous is carnal ſecurity, that Chriſt ſhould ſo importunately warn us, and affectionatly watch over us, as to this ſpiritual duty of watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; there muſt needs be much in it, when hee's ſo much upon it; and ſure, watching well, will tend greatly to our beſt wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and happineſſe, ſeeing our good Lord and Maſter makes it ſo much our buſineſſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>But what is this Goſpel duty of Watching?</head>
               <p>Firſt in general; 'tis a buſie work, &amp; much goes to the doing of it in a Goſpel way: This one work well underſtood will find us all work enough; The word
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170191:22"/>is borrowed from the practiſe of Shepherds watching over their Flocks, as <hi>Jacob</hi> over <hi>Labans;</hi> or from Souldiers upon the guard, who keep ſtrict watch; both theſe muſt diſcharge their truſt with great diligence and patience; ſpecial care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie, they muſt endure the heat by day, and the cold by night; Chriſts experienced Souldiers do find, 'tis hard duty, this; much muſt be done and ſuffered upon this account, ther's no giving over this watch, what ever it coſts us, our life lies on't:</p>
               <p>This ſpirituall watch preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes an awakened heart out of <hi>Naturall Stupiditie,</hi> and <hi>Formall Security.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Out of naturall, Carnall ſtupiditie; they cannot poſſibly watch, who were never awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the naturall man is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170191:23"/>dead, and as uncapable of this ſpirituall duty, as a man borne blind is to ſee the Sun, or a dead man to heare the thunder; he muſt firſt heare the voyce of the Son of God ſaying, awake thou that ſleepeſt, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> before he can watch with him or for him; alas, how can they watch, who have eyes and ſee not? (like the idols in the pſalm). He muſt be a ſpirituall man, that diſcernes ſpirituall things, that is fit to be a ſpirituall watch-man, and to wait in the ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Out of formal ſecuritie; A ſleepie profeſſor is ever crying, a little ſleep, a little ſlumber, &amp;c. he cannot keep his heart awake if he might have all the world, nor his eyes open; ſluggiſh ſlumbring Chriſtians are in no poſture for watching, they are as ſilly Doves without an heart; they have no heart to this heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170191:23"/>duty, and no heart in it; they are not ſpirited for this work, their ſpirituall ſenſes are bound up, they have let their watch fall, and will never take it up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without a ſound awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The watchmen muſt cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud in the eares and conſciences of ſuch, or they'l lie down to ſleep againe and againe; ſwoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſtians can never watch till the Lord rub them up to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; they had need be living and lively men, that are to watch as for life; 'tmuſt be a raiſed ſinner, and rowſed Saint, that's ſet about this work.</p>
               <p>Secondly, more particularly, Evangelical watching implyes theſe things following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Attention;<note place="margin">Iſa. 50.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> a ſpiritual watchman muſt have his eare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened morning by morning (as the prophets) that he may heare what the Spirit ſaith;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. &amp; 3.</note> this
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170191:24"/>the Spirit calls for, over and over <hi>Let him that hath an eare, he are</hi> &amp;c: he muſt have an hearing and harkening eare too, that would here the ſtill voyce, the whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the holy Spirit; he muſt have an eare to heare from God that keepes his watch, or he will have no eye to ſee him, no mouth to ſpeak from him or for him; God has much to ſay to his awakened ones, that are upon his watch, they had need have their eares about them, yea within them; An heavie eare and a ſleepie heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 6.10.</note> go together; to whom ſhall we ſpeak and give warning, (ſayes <hi>Jeremie</hi> ſadly) they have uncircumciſed eares, &amp;c: and cannot heare; alas the ſpeakers may ſhut up their mouths there,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mach.</hi> 13.15.</note> where the people ſtop their eares; they are no hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers indeed, who have eares and heare not; And may we not take
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170191:24"/>up that heavie complaint at this day (one of the ſaddeſt in all the Book of God) they have made their hearts and eares heavie;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.19.</note> leaſt they ſhould heare with their eares, &amp;c: Who ſo deafe as many of Gods Servant (to bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row that expreſſion) much preaching (as great ſounds) hath made many deafe, that what they would not heare, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; And what are the wiſeſt charmings to ſuch deafe Adders? well, Chriſts watchmen muſt be ſwift to heare, for his motions are quick; hee's ſomtimes, but a word and away; a knock, and he has done.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Intention,</hi> a watchman muſt be very intent upon his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; corporall watching, much more ſpiritual, ſhould take up our Spirits; God muſt be much heeded, and his whole work well-minded, even with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170191:25"/>whole heart, eſpecially this work of watching; Hee's no ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant for Chriſt that would ſerve him by halves; ther's no being for him almoſt, but altogether, or not at all: all our ſpirituall forces muſt be muſtred up, to keepe this watch; we muſt ſtir up all our ſtrength, and all too little in the diſcharge of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; 'twill take up the whole man; ther's no halting here, leſt evil overtake us: a lame Chriſtian will never ſtand to it, but muſt be ſitting down ever and anon. He had need be a man of another Spirit <hi>(Caleb-like)</hi> that would follow the Lord ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in this ſpirituall watch. As naturall things act to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, within their Sphear; ſo in this ſupernatural work of evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical watching, we ſhould act all we can for God,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <hi>9.10.</hi>
                  </note> within the Sphear of our ſpirituall activitie;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170191:25"/>what ever we find in our hands to do for him (eſpecially at ſo weightie and buſie a work as this) we ſhould do it with all our might; there muſt be an holy violence and fervencie, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panying Goſpel vigilancie; ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall force will doe well here, indeed we can never Watch well without it; If it once come to a Spirit of indifferencie, it will not be long, ere we be ſurprized by a Spirit of ſecuritie: if we care not much (<hi>Gallio</hi>-like) we ſhall Watch but little; a ſlothfull Spirit will be ſleepie, do what you can. Oh what ſad ſlumbrings amongſt us, ſince Chriſtians have laid themſelves down upon beds of eaſe! a lazie creature, is never likely to Watch with Chriſt or for him. Hee's nimble as a Roe; quick in his turnes; No you muſt ſtirre up your ſelves in Chriſts ſtrength, to quit your
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170191:26"/>ſelves like men in his ſervice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Inſpection. Chriſts Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men muſt be all Seers, and have ſeeing eyes, as well as hearing eares; our ſpirituall Watch lies moſt within, 'tis an inward Watch eſpecially: our eyes muſt be in our hearts and upon them; 'Tis a very conſiderable Watch word that,<note place="margin">Prov. <hi>42.3</hi>
                  </note> Above all keping keep thy heart; a ſtrong and ſtrict guard muſt be kept there; and indeed if the Watch be not kept ſtrictly there, all our watching will be invain; 'Twil be to lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle purpoſe to ſet a Watch be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our mouths, or make a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with our eyes; if the plague of the heart be not watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over, it will be ever breaking forth into putrified ſores. Had we an hundred eyes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> they had need be all at watch here, for our hearts are deceitfull above meaſure, who can know them?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170191:26"/>And he that is not faithfull in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward watching, will never be good for ought, either as to out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward waiting on God, or watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over others; How many have been looking ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, that they are to ſeeke at home? watching the haltings of others, but not their own, buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodys in other's mattters, and neglecting the buſineſſe of their own Spirits; they are eſpying motes in the eyes of others, and lay out their eyes at home, or ſee not the beames in them. How oft does the Spirit knock at their doores, and they not within? when he comes to deale with their hearts, they are not to be found; 'Twas ſaid of old, Fooles will be medling: that is, with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not themſelves; Oh, how many ſuch fools are every where, whoſe eyes are in the Corners of the Earth, ſeldome in the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170191:27"/>of their own hearts; moſt buſie, where they have leaſt to doe, and leaſt, where moſt; will not the Lord ere long ſearch ſuch as with Candles, who put out their lights within, that they may not ſee themſelves? will he not ſtorme them home, that ſcatter their wayes abroad: will not the Judge (think you) be at their doores, who are all for judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others, but not themſelves: Well; the Lord is about to find the heavie-headed and hearted Virgins work within their own doores, and to ſet them upon heart-watching againe by ſome awakening diſpenſations; Oh, 'tis one chief buſineſſe in our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall watch to try our own Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; and much communing with our ſelves will keep our hearts awake; and indeed ſince the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Criſt have idled it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and neglected this inward
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170191:27"/>work of heart-ſearching, they have left their firſt works and watchings.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Circumſpection; In this ſpiritual watch, as we ſhould have our eyes in our hearts, ſo in our heads; as to looke within, ſo without; As the Dove caſts his head about, this way and that, before ſhe take her flight; So ſhould Chriſts Doves look above them and abou, them, yea every way, before they move any way; As the heart muſt be watched o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, above all watchings; ſo there muſt be a watch over the mouth, (as over <hi>Davids</hi>); over the eye, (as over <hi>Iobs</hi>): yea over the whole man, and the whole life, As we ſhould be ever upon our Watch-Tower, to Watch at all times (being a work alwayes in ſeaſon) ſo to Watch over all things; and to take a view all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, above and below, at the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170191:28"/>right hand and the left; that we be not ſurprized any where, in any thing, at any time; As the vertuous Woman whoſe price is above Rubies,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.10.27.</note> is ſaid to look well into the ways of her houſhold; So muſt the gracious Watch-man do, he muſt bee a ſeer, an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer to his own houſe; And as the Children of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> are ſaid to have underſtanding of the times,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.32.</note> and to know what <hi>Iſrael</hi> had to do; So ſhould the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirituall Watchers, have an eye upon generation-work, an heart to it, an hand in it, ſerving their owne generation (as <hi>David</hi> did) till they fall aſleepe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 13.36</note> The ſpirituall Watchman ſhould have a diſcerning into all things; not be Eagle-eyed only in ſome things and blind as Bats in other things; but as the four beaſts, which were full of eyes within, and full of eyes before and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind too;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 4.6.</note> So ſhould they that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170191:28"/>are upon the Lords Watch, be full of eyes within and without; Alas poore ſilly Creatures that we be, we meet with a ſnare in every Creature: temptations will be crouding upon us in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry condition, we are in danger on all hands, to be defiled, or deceived; and therefore we had need watch at every turne, and have our eyes turning every way, (as the flaming ſword at the Eaſt of the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi>).<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>139.</hi>
                  </note> As the Lord who is (all eye as it were) Watches us all over; over all our thoughts, all our words, all our wayes, &amp;c: So ſhould we Watch over our ſelves, even all over at all times; our goings out and comings in, our down-ſitting and upriſing; we ſhould beſet our ſelves with a ſtrict VVatch behind and before.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Exercitation; There is much worth in this VVatch it is a very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170191:29"/>buſie imployment, full of duty, a duty in every duty; we ſhould watch at every work; a ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servant is not fit for this ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſervice, this is no work for lazy-bodies; It's not carryed on by ſitting ſtill, or looking about us; 'Tis lively work, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires a living, active, quickened Spirit; grace in the habit is not ſufficient (though in the higheſt and greateſt meaſure) to keep on foot this ſpirituall watch, no not in the leaſt and loweſt work of it; when grace is not at work, ther's no watch kept, it lies ſleeping in the ſoul, and the ſoul's aſleep too; when bodily exerciſe is laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and there's a ceſſation from motion and action, we find great propenſitie to ſlumbring and heavineſſe. 'Tis even ſo in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualls, when the acts and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of grace are ſuſpened, we are eaſily overtaken with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170191:29"/>of ſlumber. Since profeſſors have been idle, and lived at eaſe in Zion, what a ſtrange Spirit of formal ſecuritie, and ſluggiſh ſecure formalitie has ſtolen upon them, and ſtolen away their hearts too? 'Tis ſad, very ſad to ſee, how the Virgins are fallen aſleep, ſince they have been all for eaſy work; careleſſe ones have let their watch fall; they find themſelves little to do in ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and ſleepe much in ſpirit; and as they give over working, ſo they give over watching; as they ceaſe from duty, they are ſeazed upon by ſecuritie; graces muſt be exerciſed, and habits actuated, by the help of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace, that our ſpirituall watch may be mannaged and maintained. Buſie heads and hearts are moſt watchfull; if we ſtirre up the grace of Chriſt in us, it will ſtirre us up to watch with Chriſt and for him.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170191:30"/>
               <p>As appeares plainly in new-converts, who are much wrought upon, and work much; they are full of ſpirituall ſtruglings, wraſtlings, ſearchings, pantings groanings, fighings, &amp;c: Oh how watchfull are theſe new creatures when new awakened? Chriſts babes are not like other babes, in this. For they ſleepe leaſt when new-borne, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers moſt; How watchfull in prayer, and watching unto pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer?<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>45.</hi>
                  </note> their eyes even failing with looking up; watchfull in meditation, their hearts are ever bubling up, like a quick ſpring; watchfull in hearing the good word of God, to heare a good word from God; how do they hang about Chriſts lips (as it were) with both eares, for ſome drops of ſweet ſmelling myrrhe; how watchfull to enjoy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with the Father, amongſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170191:30"/>his Children, how much upon thewing after the doves of Chriſt? no company now, like the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of Chriſt, that heare his voyce. Now it is farre other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, with many ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who having un-bent their Bow of holy purpoſes and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes, (which at firſt ſeemed to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in ſtrength like <hi>Joſephs</hi>) grow remiſſe in Goſpel-dutys,<note place="margin">Gen. <hi>49.</hi>
                  </note> take their hands off from Chriſts plow and look back, grow looſe in Spirit, loſe time, let their ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents lie ruſting by them, and their graces reſting in them; how ſuddenly and ſhamefully their watch falls, as their work failes? the longer they live, the leſſe life in their Spirits and ſervice, and all things are readie to die in them, before they die: how hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily they drive, when they once give over oyling their wheeles with ſpirituall exerciſes.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170191:31"/>
               <p>'Tis an high, hard great work to watch after a ſpirituall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; they that are upon this work in good earneſt, find a great deale of good work to doe; there's much cut out to their hands; The Lord of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard will not ſuffer them to be idle upon his watch, hee'l find them awakening work: ther's head-work, hand-work, heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, tongue-work, life-worke; ther's work within and without, at home and abroad, their own and others, for this life and a better, there's work enough to keepe one awake; And the more we work, in theſe ſpiritual ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of faith, love, deſires, &amp;c: the more watchfull we ſhall be, and the better watchmen, and workmen.</p>
               <p>And therefore the Lord will find new work for old idle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors (if he delight in them)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170191:31"/>hee'l bring ſlumbring Virgins to Soul-travel again, and awaken them to purpoſe, they'l feele ſuch hard labour therein, as will be hard to ſleep upon; And when loitering Servants fall once to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour again heartily in Gods har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, how they'l ſweat at it, and do moſt and beſt at laſt; when they ſee, how much work they have to do in a little time, how they'l work and watch, and watch in work?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Expectation. Souldiers upon the watch, wait in expectation, either of an enemie to approach or a friend to appeare, that they may be in a poſture of oppoſition or reception, to reſiſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and to relieve their friends; ſo in this ſpirituall watch, we muſt be daily in expectation of our enemies, who will be upon us on a ſudden; and if they take us at unawares, we are in an ill
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170191:32"/>taking (as we uſe to ſay) 'twill bee to our great prejudice and their advantage; An enemie not looked for, will be beforehand with us, and will hurt us moſt when we can leaſt help our ſelves; 'Tis a time he would chuſe of all other, when he is leaſt expected; as knowing, he ſhall be leaſt reſiſted. Our adverſary watches our ſlumbring times moſt, that he may take us nap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and take what he pleaſes from us; and therefore we muſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver watch in expectation of him, that he may never come unlook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for: nothing will more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearten and diſappoint him. Our expectation fruſtates his; our unwearied watchings will wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie him out; whereas, it is a faire invitation to the envious one, to lay aſide our expectation of him, who likes beſt to come unlooked for, and is moſt to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170191:32"/>ſuſpected, when he is leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected.</p>
               <p>We muſt be in expectation alſo of our beſt ſpiritual friend, who comes oft skipping like a Roe, and loves ſomtimes to take us on the ſuddain, to ſee how we are provided: He hath given us a faire warning, ſaying, Behold I come like a thief, that) is, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, ſuddenly) in the night; that we may ever have him upon our hearts, and he may not come in an hour, when we think not of him. Such a bleſſed gueſt would not come unlooked for, whoſe viſits are ſo gracious, his love ſo precious; we are like to loſe much of the ſweet and comfort of holy and happie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, if we wait little on him and for him; hee'l not tarry long, where he is not long looked for and longingly; there he comes and goes ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170191:33"/>he thinks himſelf nothing-well or welcom there, where his company is not looked for; he takes it for a great neglect of him, when we doe not expect him, and hee will not be long or much there, where he is little looked for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What are the ſpeciall times for a Chriſtians Spirituall watch?</head>
               <p>As all Chriſtians ſhould watch, ſo at all times; there is a time for all things under the Sun, but no time to loſe in ſpirituall ſlumber: there's not a ſpare-minute for ſinfull ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; a Chriſtian muſt never give over working, watching, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; his labours in the Lord muſt end with his life, when he dyes in the Lord; and his watch muſt not fall, till he fall aſleepe in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> This in general, but more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170191:33"/>
               <p n="1">1. In times of ſpiritual deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Lord has with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn his ſpirit and grace, and ſeemes to be aſleepe and ſilent to us; oh then 'tis high time to call upon our ſelves, ſaying Awake, awake; and to cry mightily to the Lord, to awake and keep not ſilence; When our beloved is going, then 'tis time (as we love him and our own Soules) to ſtirr up our ſtrength, to take hold of him, and not let him goe for a world; does he begin to eſtrange himſelf from us, Oh cry heartily to him in their language, oh thou hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> why ſhould'ſt thou be a ſtranger, as a waifaring man that tarryes but for a night, &amp;c? Thou art in the mid'ſt of us, oh leave us not; Woe unto us, when he ſhall depart from us: how many evils will come when he goes away? We have all good, in the chiefeſt Good, and all
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170191:34"/>evil without him; 'Tis loſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable to want him, whoſe abſence nothing in Heaven or Earth can make up: if he ſay, Depart from mee, there will be a corner of Hell in it here, as it will be the very Hell in Hell hereafter, Depart ye curſed, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Woe and alas unto us, for we have ſadly ſinned away his gracious preſence as ever any people did, by careleſſe ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, and carnal ſecuritie; how oft hath he found us ſlugging it upon beds of eaſe, when his fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger has been put in at the hole of the door? VVe have made him wait, till his head hath been filled with dew,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 5.2.</note> and his locks with the drops of the night; and yet we have not opened the door to him, neither for his importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor becauſe he is our friend. Had it beene an enemie or a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170191:34"/>ſtranger had done thus, he could have borne it; but that his own familiar friends ſhould lift up the heel againſt him; that ever they ſhould prove ſo hard-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt ſo tender-hearted a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; this goes to the heart in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. And now our Beloved ſtands behind the wall, as one highly offended, that will ſcarce look at thoſe, that have ſhut their eyes againſt his light, and their hearts againſt his love; this glorious Sun covers himſelf as with a Cloud, becauſe we ſleepe out the ſhinings of his light, and ſlumber out ſweet breathing-times ſhamefully, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the ſight of the Sun; and leaves us under thick ſpirituall darkneſſe (even ſuch as may be felt) and we are covered as with a Cloud in his anger; And ſhall we not now awake, and cry after him with open mouth, heart,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170191:35"/>eyes, ſaying as the daughters of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Whither is our beloved gone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.1.</note> whither is he turned aſide? Oh return, return, make haſte our Beloved, and be thou like a young Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> upon the Mountains of ſpices;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.14.</note> Oh why ſhould we be, as they that are vailed, and turn aſide, &amp;c? Ah, the longer he is abſent from us, the worſe it will be with us every day; and the greater diſtance from him, the greater our unhappineſſe: Oh then, as the two Diſciples, when the Lord <hi>Jeſus</hi> made as if he would goe further, conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſaying, <hi>Abide with us, for 'tis towards evening,</hi> &amp;c: So now when he carries ſtrange to us, makes as if he would away, and carry all away with him too; we ſhould even lay hands on him, and hold him by an humble holy force, ſaying, <hi>Abide with us, for 'tis towards evening;</hi> &amp;c: The day declines.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170191:35"/>
               <p n="2">2. In times of ſpiritual de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion: When noble Vines prove degenerate Plants, when Stars fall from Heaven; when many begin in the Spirit, and end in the fleſh. Oh then we had need be upon our ſpiritual watch, and take ſpecial heed to our ſpirits; when ſo many loſe firſt life and love, and leave their firſt works; we had need have our eyes about us, yea within us, and look into our own hearts, leſt we be at a loſſe there too, and coole within; when ſo many fall away. <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtands, take heed leaſt he fall;</hi> 'Tis a time of (almoſt) an uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal conſumption in Spirituals; never ſo great decayes in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; Chriſtians Spirits faile and fall ſadly; Stomack's gone, every where, to the beſt ſood; little ſpiritual Palate is left in any to relliſh the ſweet ſavour
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170191:36"/>of Chriſts precious Oyntments, all ſpiritual ſenſes dull and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie; And ſhall we not now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake? feele our own pulſes; conſult with ſpirituall Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and make diligent uſe of all quickning and ſtrengthning meanes of grace, leſt we alſo be left under the ſame ſpiritual lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhings, and have wofull occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to cry out another day, Our leanneſſe, our leanneſſe?</p>
               <p n="3">3. When an hour of ſpiritual Temptation is upon us, when many are led Captive by ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual wickedneſſes; Oh then that Counſel is moſt ſeaſonable, <hi>Be vigilant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe your adverſary the Devill as a Roaring Lion, walketh about, ſeeking whom he may devour;</hi> 'Tis not for us to ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, when Satan Watches; nor to ſhut our eyes, when hee's running up and down with open mouth; how eaſily may he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170191:36"/>make a prey of us; when we lie ſleeping at his, Feet? The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is come down with great rage, he will be worſt at laſt, and doe much miſchief in a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time; and if the envious one find us aſleep, when he is moſt awakned, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over us for evill, what a world of evil vvill he bring upon us? what havock will he make amongſt us, yea within us? what tares will he ſow? If Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan belet looſe, hee will be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with all power and policie; and if he find us at a looſe end, ſleeping idlely in the Devils ſhop; hee'l be very buſie with us, and ſet us aworke to our own woe; we may expect, a flood of ſtrong deluſions, and ſtrange temptations will be iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of his wide mouth, which gapes for us; and if we lie ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his way, we ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170191:37"/>away in theſe filthy ſtreames, like dead fiſh; The Prince of darkneſſe is broke out, and ſmoak is broak out of the bottom leſſe pit with him; there's great danger of being loſt in it, or choked by it, eſpecially if we walk as blind men in a ſpirituall ſleep.</p>
               <p>Oh what need then to awake (if ever) and to call upon the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> to awake, and reſcue his darlings from the mouth of this roaring Lyon, to ariſe for his prey, to divide the ſpoil with the mightie, and to lead captivitie captive; If we lie down to ſleep now with fold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed armes, leaving the guide of our ſpirits, and he leave us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to the miſguidings of our owne deceitfull hearts, how will the ſubtle Serpent deceive us at every turn, and turne us out of the way, to the right hand
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170191:37"/>or to the left; eſpecially now the old experienced deceiver, <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms himſelf into an Angel of light</hi> that he may drive on his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cooſening trade, the more myſteriouſly and miſchievouſly, putting darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe. Why then, 'tis more then time to awake out of ſleep, to get our ſpirits quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up by the influence of Gods good Spirit, and to muſter up all our ſpirituall forces, ſpeedily and ſtrenuouſly, putting <hi>on the whole armour of God</hi> on the right hand, and on the left; that we may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil on all hands, in this evill day, <hi>and having done all to ſtand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In times of great expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: When we look for great things from Heaven, when <hi>Zion</hi> is in travel for glorious Births, when precious promiſes are nigh
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170191:38"/>accompliſhment,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jool.</hi> 3.18</note> 
                  <hi>the Mountaines readie to drop new Wine, and the Hills to flow with milk;</hi> As, the Spirits powering out like floods, &amp;c: A Spirit of Life i'th wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and a voice out of the Clouds, ſaying, Come up hither; <hi>A Nation to be borne at once!</hi> Is it not time to cry, Awake, awake, the glory of the Lord is riſing, &amp;c: Oh ſhould we not look with both eyes, and liſten with both eares, to heare when it ſhall be ſaid;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jſai.</hi> 66.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing, who hath ſeen ſuch things? ſhall the earth be made to bring forth in one day?</hi> Were it not great pitty to ſleep out the awakening providences that are upon us, making way to fulfill ſuch glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes? Is not this the language of awakened Saints, crying, <hi>Awake, awake, put on ſtrength thou Arme of the Lord, as in the dayes of Old,</hi> &amp;c: and ſhall
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170191:38"/>we now cry, A little ſleep, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſlumber, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> God forbid; Oh now, now, the Lords remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers muſt <hi>give him no reſt,</hi> nor reſt day or night under a ſpirit of ſlumber, <hi>'till Jeruſalem be made a praiſe in the Earth,</hi> and the Reſt of his feet be glorious.</p>
               <p>'Tis the common cry amongſt Gods people (when they are in ſtraits, and at a ſtand) <hi>Awake, O Lord, why ſleepeſt thou?</hi> When as alas, 'tis they that are aſleep, and muſt be awakened (or they'l be nonplus'd ever and anon) and aſſoon as they are awakned, they'l ſee it and ſay ſo; We won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the work goes on no faſter, and that the Lord does no more for us; whereas 'tis a wonder, he has wrought ſo much for us, or does any thing at all for our good, who are grovvn ſo heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170191:39"/>heartleſſe, careleſſe under mercies.</p>
               <p>However, his work goes on in his own way, whether we ſleep or wake; for his heart is upon't and he <hi>neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps,</hi> but is running his courſasa Gyant refreſhed with Wine, and will leave his ſlumbring Servants be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, to follow him with ſhame and ſorrow; <hi>The Ancient of dayes,</hi> will keep his time, not loſe a day, nor miſſe a minute (howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we loſe time); And hee'l, give a good account one day, what he has been doing for his poore Children, when they will not be able to anſwer one of a thouſand, for their ſlumbrings and wandrings.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When the Lord looks for great things from us, having done great things for us, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded mighty ſalvations, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170191:39"/>choiſe mercies, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended peculiar Goſpel-bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to us, and all by a ſtrong hand through wonders of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; Now when and where the Lord does much, ſo much; then and there he looks for much very much. He may well call us to an account, at ſuch a time, and ſay, <hi>What doe you more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers?</hi> Special mercy may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge ſingular duty;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.47</note> He has been at extraordinary charge and coſt with us, and he expects more then ordinary in our ſpirits and ſervices; Tis not for us to ſerve him with that which coſts us nought; when we have coſt him ſo deare; one would think, the weight of ſuch obligations lying upon us, ſhould effectually awaken us, to look up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for ſuch a ſuitable and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable communication of his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170191:40"/>Spirit and grace, as may more clearly informe us in that high and heavenly leſſon, (moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the day) and more fully enable us to take it out; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to <hi>walk worthy of the Lord unto all pleaſing, being fruitfull in every good work,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10.</note> &amp;c: A low Spirit, and lazie ſervices are moſt unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to high and mighty diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, and will be moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable; ſhall we do leaſt for him, when he has done moſt for us? Has he watched over us, and his eyes been alwayes upon us, <hi>from the beginning of the yeare unto the end?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.12.</note> and ſhall we ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber now like ſlothfull Servants, as if we had neither eyes to ſee him working for us, nor hands to work for him? ſhall living mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies lie dead by us, and we dying in the midſt of them, offering up the dead in ſacrifice to the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170191:40"/>God, who has given us our lives for a prey? ſhall we <hi>thus requite the Lord like a fooliſh people and unwiſe?</hi> will it not be ill ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at our hands that we ſhould be worſt to him, when hee's beſt to us? No wonder, if he withhold his Spirit, when we thus grieve, tempt, and quench it by a Spirit of ſecuritie; how can we look for other, but that he ſhould be taking away his Golden Candleſtick,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.6</note> and the light too, when ſo many do little elſe, but play or ſleep by it? We muſt not think to lie alwaies ſleeping with the breaſt i'th mouth: he will be covering the bleſſed paps, girt about with a Golden Girdle.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170191:41"/>
               <head>Application by way of Information.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Is it a Goſpel-duty to watch? then ſee the neceſſitie of an awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening Miniſtrie; in ſuch a ſleepie age as this; there was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more need of awakened and awakening overſeers to watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, to lift up their voyce like a Trumpet, cry to aloud and ſpare not,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11</note> ſaying, Awake; oh what need of <hi>goads and nailes to be faſtened in our ſides, and upon our hearts by the maſters of the aſſemblies from that one Shepherd?</hi> 'Tis time for <hi>wiſdome to cry in the Streets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20 8.4.</note> 
                  <hi>to utter her voyce in the chief places of concourſe,</hi> ſaying, unto you, O men, I call, &amp;c: When the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins ſlumber thus, both the wiſe and fooliſh; 'twill be a great mercy to have the Word of the Lord, as a hammer at our doores yea as a fire within us; and to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170191:41"/>feele the ſword of the Spirit pricking us to the very heart, o keep us awake in Spirit, when ſo many are heavie with ſleep there: There was never more work, then now, for the Sons of thunder; Ah, that Spirit of ſlumber that is fallen upon this generation, will make work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, for all the faithfull watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, throughout the Nation; And me-thinks, the ſtrong ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings, of ſo many ſleepie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, ſhould exceedingly ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and awaken thoſe that watch for Souls; 'Tis not for them to ſlumber of all others, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ſuch a time, when ſo many lie ſleeping round about them: Oh woe, woe to <hi>the blind Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, the dumb Dogs that cannot bark ſleeping, lying down,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10.</note> 
                  <hi>loving to ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;</hi> who make beds of eaſe for bedrid ſpirits, and ſow Pillows to ſluggards arm-holes, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170191:42"/>ſmooth things, to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that love to have it ſo, that are all for eaſie propheſie, or none at all; Oh then let all the watchmen of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whom the Lord hath ſet upon the Watch-Tower, <hi>Watch and Pray,</hi> and preach in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon, and give the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple warning of this hour of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, whether they will heare, or whether they will forbear, that they may deliver their own Souls, and happily recover others alſo from the ſnare of the Devil, who are (aſleep in his armes and) taken captive by him at his will; And let all the Lords peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple highly prize and heartily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect an heart-awakening, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quickening Miniſtrie, and welcome that word moſt, which comes moſt ſtirringly home, and is moſt ſoundly ſet on by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Spirit.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170191:42"/>
               <p n="2">2. Is it a Goſpel-Duty to Watch? then what a ſpecial mercy is it at this day, to have an awakened heart. The Keeper of <hi>Iſrael</hi> Watches very graciouſly over thoſe, he keeps watchfull; 'Tis no common favour to be kept alive at ſuch a dead time; ſure the Father of mercies looks moſt ſweetly to thoſe Children, and will ſmile moſt lovingly upon them, whom he cauſes to lie broad-waken, looking after him; Oh bleſſed be his name, that he reſerves a little remnant by him, waiting on him, and for him; What would become of us all, if a few were not upon their watch, would not the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake to judgment, were all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep about him, and none a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked to cry for mercy? would not he lay about to purpoſe, did not ſome hold his hands, by lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up their hands and hearts to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170191:43"/>Heaven? Is he not readie to ſay, Let me alone, that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume them? and is he not let a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by all, but an handfull of wraſtling Saints that have got within him? would he not be gone, (think you) but that his deare ones watch him, cry migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily after him, and will not let him goe? Nay, is he not going about to take his glory, Spirit, grace, Goſpel, and all away with him? 'Tis well for us there are ſome watching, waiting, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, about the bed of <hi>Solomon,</hi> (loath to let him goe) <hi>valiant men,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
                  <hi>even the valiant of</hi> Iſrael; Oh happie Souls, that lie ever upon this heavenly watch, who watch the more, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſo many ſlumber; It will goe well with them, how ill ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver things go, for,
<list>
                     <item>1. They are neereſt mercy of all other; if any ſweet influences fall from Heaven, <hi>they are waiting
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170191:43"/>with mouths wide open,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job.</hi> 29.23.</note> 
                        <hi>as for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rain</hi> (as of old they waited for <hi>Job.</hi>) If the Sun of righteouſneſſe ariſe, they are like to ſee him firſt; if his light ſhine, their eyes are open; and if his love breathe, their hearts are open; if good reports come, to make the bones fat, who but they will heare, who are ever hearke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? When ever the Lord ſhall open the door of hope, they are next hand; when the day breaks and the ſhadows flee away, they'l be the bleſſed ſpectators, who watch more then they that watch for the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; If the Spirit be powred forth as floods, who'l drink ſo deep as theſe gaping thirſtie Souls? When ever the King ſits at table, and cauſes the ſpikenard to ſend forth a ſweet ſmell, they muſt needs feele the ſavour of his oyntments, who wait as Olive-Plants
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170191:44"/>round about his table, when ever bleſſings are handed out, they are within reach; Oh 'tis a rich mercy to be heereſt mercy.</item>
                     <item>2. They are fitteſt for Duty. Is there any work to do for God, his Cauſe, his People, they are neer hand, waiting for it, ſaying, What wilt thou have us do Lord? If a word of Command come, 'tis welcome, they are up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Watch: If the Lord ſay, Come, they come; and if he ſay, Go, they go; their loyns are girt. If the King of glory look out, and cry, Who is on my ſide? who? they are ready to look out of the window towards him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.2</note> ſaying, Here are we, Lord. They are called to his foot (as the man of the Eaſt) onely wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a word from his mouth: they ſet themſelves in a poſture on purpoſe, to follow the Lamb
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170191:44"/>whitherſoever he goeth. Yea, awakened hearts, whoſe eyes have ſeen the King in his beauty have and holy ambition in them to do as much, and as well in their Maſters ſervice, as he ſhall give them power to do, of his good pleaſure: Whereas the ſlothful ſervant is ever to ſeeke both in will and power, when his Maſter has work for him; he will either ſlip out of the way or ſleep at work. If Jeſus Chriſt call oth' ſudden, and have any haſte of work, hee's all ungirt, and will be ſo long a getting ready, till the buſineſſe might be half done: But the vigilant diligent ſervant, is at an houres warning; he is the veſſel unto honour, meet for the Maſters uſe and prepared for every good work.</item>
                     <item>3. They are like to be richeſt in experience; this muſt needs
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170191:45"/>be men of great obſervation, whoſe eyes are ever open to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the gracious and glorious goings of God in Providences and Ordinances; He will make moſt of his glory and <hi>goodneſſe to paſse before thoſe,</hi> that watch and wait according to his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 3 3.19.22.</note> (as <hi>Moſes</hi> upon the Rock.) They'l meet with many choiſe pledges of divine love, many drops of myrrhe from Chriſts fingers, and Kiſſes from his lips, that watch at his feet; his ſteps will drop fatneſſe upon ſuch as lie in his way, waiting for him; Hee'l lay up much of his Heavenly treaſure in holy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakned hearts, and reveale moſt of his ſecrets to his hearkening, hidden ones;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 13.52.</note> The watchfull, faithfull Stewards will have out of thier <hi>treaſure to bring forth, new and old;</hi> they'l have all manner of pleaſant fruits laid up at their
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170191:45"/>gates for the Beloved;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.13.</note> they will be able to give the beſt account, what God does for their Souls, who watch their own hearts beſt and wait moſt for him there; He will be much with them, whom he finds much at home, and make out much of himſelf to them; Watchfull <hi>Iſraelites</hi> will be the beſt provided of hidden <hi>Mannah,</hi> they'l be before-hand with all others, in reſpect of the moſt experience, and beſt intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, from Heaven.</item>
                     <item>4. They are readieſt for the appearance of Chriſt. If he come, at morning, or even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, mid-day or mid-night, at what watch ſoever he comes, they are watching; yea when they ſleep, their heart waketh;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2.</note> they are readie to goe forth to meet the bridgroome,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 25.6</note> ſhould he call at midnight; and his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will be moſt welcom, where
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170191:46"/>it has been moſt waited for; What an happie and heavenly poſture was good old <hi>Simeon</hi> in,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.25.26.27.28.</note> to meet Chriſt in the Temple, who had ſo long waited in the Spirit for the conſolation of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> how ready was he, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that bleſſed Child with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen armes and heart too? where was Chriſt more welcom, then to little <hi>Zachaeus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk</hi> 19.3.4 5.</note> who was got upon this Watch-Tower (the Sycamor-Tree) deſiring to ſee him, how ſweetly was Chriſts heart affected towards this poore waiting Soul? he looks up with a loving eye, to ſatisfie his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing looks; and how happie doth this good man think himſelf in ſo bleſſed a gueſt; he received him joyfully.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 24.28</note> Oh how readie will the quick-ſighted Eagles be to gather about him, whoſe eyes are ever looking towards this riſing Sun? <hi>Behold I come quickly,</hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170191:46"/>ſaith he: <hi>Amen;</hi> ſay they,<note place="margin">Rev. 22.20.</note> 
                        <hi>Even ſo, come Lord Jeſus.</hi> Obſerve, how ſweetly that lovely word <hi>(Amen)</hi> is couched betwixt them, and their hearts together in it!</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Uſe of Examination.</head>
               <p>Let us give our Souls a viſit in the Name of the Lord, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mune ſecretly and ſeriouſly with our own hearts about our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Watch.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diſcoveries of Spiritual Slumber.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Is the Lord ſilent to thee, who hath uſed to ſpeak much to thy heart, to beſpeak it? Doſt thou heare ſeldom from him? will he ſcarce give thee a word? why then thou mayeſt be jealous of thy ſelf, that thy heart is aſleep; for he will have
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170191:47"/>a mouth to ſpeak, where there is an ear to hear. Canſt thou not remember the moneths of old, when he gave in many words in ſeaſon? has he not oft ſpoke to thy heart, when man ſpoke to thy ear? And does he now keep ſilence? Doſt thou onely hear the voyce of a man now; and ſo runnes to <hi>Ely,</hi> (as <hi>Samuel</hi> did)? Doſt thou hear much without, and little or nothing within? Does not thine ear affect thy heart? Is not the Word as a fire within thee? doſt thou hang upon the bare outward admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, and art thou a ſtranger to the glorious miniſtration of the Spirit? Why, ſure thy Watch is down, and he ſeems to ſlumber. And now he hides his ear from thy breathing: thou cryeſt, and he will not anſwer thee. Ask thy ſoul ſolemnly, What's the matter? is his ear
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170191:47"/>heavy? Is there not a cauſe within? is not thy heart heavy? Has not he called, and thou haſt not heard? has not he knocked, and thou not opened? Is it not thus, O ſlumbring Soul? ſpeak out, and tell the Lord how it is within.</item>
                  <item>2. Art not thou ſilent before the Lord, who uſedſt to cry migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily after him? Is not thine heart ſhut up now, which thou was wont to pour forth? thy ſighings come not before the Lord, as they have done, and thy groanings are hid from him. Art not thou a ſtranger to thy own cloſet, where thou haſt much ſought him in ſecret? Surely thy heart is fallen into a dead ſleep; 'tis a ſad ſwooning-time with thy ſluggiſh ſpirit: how haſt thou loſt thy heart in point of love to prayer, and life in it? Oh wer'ſt thou throughly awakened, thou
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170191:48"/>wouldſt not for a world give over this thriving Trade of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual begging: thou couldſt not keep ſo long out of his preſence, who hath given thee ſo many ſweet viſits in prayer:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Job</hi> 27.10.</note> the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite will not pray alwaies: and 'tis no wonder, for he cannot pray at all in Gods account: But that a true Iſraelite, who has had power with God in prayer, ſhould ceaſe to pour out a prayer before him; this is ſtrange, and yet no more ſtrange then true amongſt ſlumbring Chriſtians, who cannot chuſe but give over praying, when they give over watching: the Spirit of prayer muſt needs be ſilent under a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſlumber.</item>
                  <item>3. Is not thy Spiritual warfare maintained? doſt not thou wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle againſt ſpiritual wickedneſs, &amp;c? Doſt thou not feel the Law of the mind warring againſt the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170191:48"/>Law in thy members? Art thou not at odds with thy own heart every day, and quarrelling with it for heart-ſins? Why then the heart is aſleep, whileſt thy luſts lie ſleeping within thee; thou doſt not watch, whileſt thou doſt not war. How ſhamefully wilt thou be foiled by the luſts thou fighteſt not againſt? Sin will get head and heart too, whiles thy heart is aſleep: thy luſts like ſo many flies will ſwarm about thy ſleepie ſoul. Thou doſt not reckon with thy ſelf about thy dying to ſin, ſelf, &amp;c. Alas, how dead is thy heart in the mean time? thou haſt given over thy complaining of the body of death, and yet thy luſts are more lively; and thou liveleſſe: they ſtrong, and thou art weak: ſure, they are awake, and thou ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</item>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170191:49"/>
                  <item>4. Art not thou ſenſible of the ſubtile inſinuations, and ſecret ſuggeſtions of Satan, in this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie day of his? Doſt thou meet with none of his buffettings, now he layes ſo about him? doſt thou feel none of his fiery darts, now Hell is broke looſe? Mayſt thou not be very ſuſpitious, that a ſpirit of ſlumber is upon thee, and the evill ſpirit rocks thee? Art not thou pleaſing thy ſelf with ſmooth things, lying quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon a pillow of carnal ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and Satan pleaſing of thee too, and loath to diſquiet thee? Art thou at eaſe in Zion, ſinging a <hi>Requiem</hi> to thy Soul? why thou mayſt ſleep on for him, and take thy reſt. 'Tis not for his purpoſe to awaken us out of falſe dreams: this cunning Fowler is moſt buſie with awakened ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits that are ſtruggling from him, that would be ever upon the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170191:49"/>wing Chriſtward; but he ſtirs little, when men lie aſleep at his feet, onely watches over them: he makes leaſt noyſe there, but does moſt hurt. Oh the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of iniquitie works moſt and worſt, amongſt idle ſouls, that work not, watch not.</item>
                  <item>5. Doſt not thou ſympathize with the ſuffering ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt? Is not thy heart affected with <hi>the afflictions of Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph?</hi> Haſt thou little or no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of thy brethrens ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities? Canſt not bleed in their wounds as thine own heart, whoſe blood has been ſpilt like water upon the ground, for the teſtimony of of Jeſus? Sure, then thy ſpirit within thee is benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med under a ſpirit of ſecurity; and almoſt paſt feeling. Did not the ſad cryes of the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Proteſtants, in the Valleys of <hi>Piedmont</hi> and in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170191:50"/>Have pity upon us, O our Friends, have pity upon us, for the hand of the Lord hath touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us: Did not (I ſay) their doleful complaints come to thine ears, and did not this go to thine heart? do not thy bowels ſound within thee towards them who are ſighing it out, Our bowels, our bowels? doſt thou not make lamentation over them, crying, Alas, alas? Is it nothing to thee, there are ſo many mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Zion at this day hanging their harps upon the Willowes? and doſt thou put no tears i'th bottle for them?</item>
               </list>
               <p>And further, how ſtands thy heart affected towards ſuch as are afflicted in ſpirit? Does not thy ſoul bleed within thee to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards poor wounded ſouls, who are even ready to bleed to death for want of the gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Lord of life? Canſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170191:50"/>thou not mourn in ſecret, for ſuch as walk mournfully without the Sun? Time was, when thine head was as water, and thy eyes as fountains of tears, that thou couldſt not but weep with thoſe that wept, and mourn (as the Doves of the valleys) with them that mourned: but now thy eyes are dry, thy bowels ſtrait, and thy heart hard. Oh what ſtrong ſtupidity is upon thee? if all the members ſhould ſuffer, when but one ſuffers? how ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid and ſenſeleſſe is that one, that ſuffers not when ſo many ſuffer? I cannot but pity ſuch ſlumbring Chriſtians, who want yearning bowels of pitty, when I conſider, what ſharp medicines muſt be applyed to their inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſtupified ſpirits, to cut them to the quick, and fetch up their ſpiritual ſenſes, to ſympathize with Chriſt in his members.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170191:51"/>
               <p n="6">6. Is not thy Soul vexed at the filthy converſation of the ungodly,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.7, 8.</note> as <hi>Lots</hi> righteous Soul was? Doſt thou not bear the backſlidings of Gods own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, was a burthen upon thine heart before the Lord? Doſt thou not inwardly tremble at the diſhonour put upon that Name which hath been proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med amongſt us, in ſo loud lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages as glorious in holineſſe, &amp;c? Are not the abominations of the Times the very abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thy ſoul? Canſt thou not mourn in ſecret, for the open Pride, prophaneneſſe, profuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſo many thouſands in our Iſrael at this day? Why then, (believe it) thy heart is aſleep indeed, when the crying ſins of this adulterous generation do not awaken it.</p>
               <p>Oh how many, who have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared <hi>as Children of the day, have
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170191:51"/>fellowſhip now with the unfruitfull works of darkneſſe?</hi> who once ſeemed white as ſnow, and are now black as a coal; who ſome years ſince would not have tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the garment ſpotted with the fleſh, have now put on the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> skin again, and the Leopards ſpots; having once eſcaped the pollutions of the fleſh, and are again entangled therewith.</p>
               <p>Hovv are the honourable things of the Law, and Goſpel too, become contemptible in the eyes of many, who ſeemed to prize them above thouſands of gold and ſilver? how are the precious pearls of Jeſus Chriſt, which are worth more then a world, and of which the World is not worthy, trampled under foot, as if they were nothing worth. Oh what loathing of Manna, even amongſt Iſraelites?
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170191:52"/>what turning of grace into wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſſe? Horrible things are done in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that in the ſight of the Sun, publiſhed in the <hi>ſtreets of Aſhkelon, ſo that the daughters of the uncircumciſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph?</hi> And ſhall not the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Zion</hi> ſigh and mourn for theſe abominations, which are more then enough to break ones ſleep, and heart too, which break the Lords own heart: And if thou lay them not to heart,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9.</note> thy heart's aſleep.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Directions for Watchfulneſſe.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Even ſet before thee; the All-ſeeing eye of <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which is ever upon thee; His eyes, which are ten thouſand times brighter then the Sun, daily looked upon by an eye of Faith, will be very awakening; Think much upon thoſe heart-ſtirring
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170191:52"/>meditations,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 139.1.2, 3, 4.</note> of Gods glorious preſence, which were ſo much upon <hi>Davids</hi> heart; as, Gods en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing thy path and thy bed, beſetting thee behind and before looking thee thorough in all places, at all times; watching over every thought of thy heart, every word of thy tongue, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> Oh ſay oft within thy ſelf in the goings out and comings in <hi>Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I goe from thy preſence</hi> &amp;c? The keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who neither ſlumbers nor ſleepes, looks upon thee in all thy ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings, with a broad eye; thou art never out of his ſight, ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or waking; hee never looks off of thee; How ſoundly was <hi>Jacob</hi> rowſed out of ſleep, upon the apprehenſion of Gods dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.16 17.</note> He <hi>awaked out of ſleep, and ſaid, The Lord is in this place, and I knew it not,</hi> &amp;c: Had I been aware of him, I had been
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170191:53"/>awake. Serious thoughts of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching glory, will put one beſide their ſleep, and ſtartle one to purpoſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.21.22.</note> 
                  <hi>Heare yee not mee (ſaith the Lord)</hi> and <hi>will you not tremble at my preſence?</hi> Why then, 'tis becauſe you <hi>have eyes, and ſee not; eares and heare not;</hi> holy tremblings will prevent heavie ſlumbrings; Oh that our drowſie Spirits, were continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally over-awed with the deep meditations of the omniſcience and omnipreſence of the Father of Spirits, how effectually would they be awakened out of carnall and formal ſecuritie? The eyes of Gods glory looking full upon us, will keep open the eyes of our heads, and hearts too; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of God will cleare up our ſpiritual ſight, and quicken it. Well, his eyes are alwaies upon ours, and his heart goes along with ours, what need have
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170191:53"/>we of Watchfull eyes and hearts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Wait for the glorious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Spirit, under e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very outward adminiſtration; This charge is given to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.3.</note> by him which had the ſeven Spirits of God, walking in the midſt of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks, when he would earneſtly provoke them to watchfullneſſe, threatning to come upon them as a thief, if they did not watch: <hi>Let him that hath an eare, heare what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches;</hi> This bleſſed Counſel is recommended ſeven times, in two Chapters, to adde the greater weight to it, and to make deeper impreſſion. Oh ſet that ſtone with ſeven eyes, before thine eyes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken them and ſpirit them:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.9.</note> All the workings of the eternal Spirit upon our ſpirits are awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening;
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170191:54"/>when ever the word comes with life, in the power of the Spirit, it will raiſe us out of ſpiritual ſlumbers: Indeed a lower or leſſe diſpenſation will not doe it; Oh how dead we lie at pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, hearing, reading, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> till the Spirit of life breathe upon us; we are little moved, when the Spirit moves not; All's but as <hi>Eliſha's</hi> ſtaffe upon the Child, there was neither voyce nor hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 4.31.</note> but if the holy Spirit ſtretch himſelf upon us, his eyes upon ours, (as it were), then our eyes will be opened; How eaſie a thing is it, to lie ſleeping and ſlumbring in and under any Forme, where there is no power; how dead we lie by the letter and it by us, without the Spirit?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.37.1.2.</note> Oh how heartleſſe and Spirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe are moſt profeſſors at this day, as the very dry bones in the open valley, reſting and ruſting
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170191:54"/>in outward forms, not feeling inward povver; and there they may reſt till they rot, and lie till they die, if the Spirit do not breathe upon them, as upon thoſe dry bones. How many of Chriſts witneſſes are ſpiritually dead, taking up in the letter without life? and in this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitable, uncomfortable poſture will they lie languiſhing under ſpirituall Lethargies and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, till the ſpirit of life from God enter into them. That bleſſed reſurrection of the ſpirits of the Saints, out of the grave of formality and ſecurity, which is more to be deſired a thouſand times then their raiſing up in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and glory it'h world, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a plentiful effuſion, and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull operation of the holy Spirit, may not be expected, cannot be effected; If the Spirit of judgment and burning fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170191:55"/>their hearts, it will fire them out of formalitie, and ſtartle them out of ſecuritie; when he ſhall come down, with a ſound from Heaven, as with a mighty ruſhing wind, upon the ſluggiſh Spirits of the Slumbring Virgins, how will they be awakened to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, as the Apoſtles were, when the <hi>Holy Ghoſt reſted as fire upon them,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be diligent, frequent, and fervent in ſpiritual Exerciſes, if you would keep up your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Watch. Conſtant, conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious diſcharge of duty, will be a ſpecial remedy againſt cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary formality, and carnall ſecurity; pure Religion is no idle Trade; 'twill find us work enough (can we but find in our hearts to fall to it) and that full of variety and excellency, to keep us awake and at work all our dayes. 'Tis not for want of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170191:55"/>work that any ſtand idle in the Lords vineyard, but for want of will to it. 'Tis a very buſie time with Jeſus Chriſt, his heart is upon his work; and 'tis ſo with his waiting-ſervants too, for his work is upon their hearts: and they that are lazie and ſleepy-headed now, are like the Slug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that ſleeps in harveſt, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leaſt to do, where there is moſt work: And they are ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervants above all other, who are moſt ſleepie, when they ſhould do the moſt and beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. How buſie will the Devil be with ſuch drouſie ones, and hardeſt at work with them, while they are at eaſie work, to caſt them into a dead ſleep? His work goes on, where ours ceaſes: how much Work have we found Satan in theſe dayes, by neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods work? Since we have left our firſt Work, we have left
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170191:56"/>our firſt Watch: and we find it now vvork more then enough to keep our ſouls awake. Omiſſion of ſpirituall duties hath brought upon us an habitual indiſpoſition to duties, that we find no heart to them, feel little heart or heat in them; Since Chriſtians have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>girt their loyns, and ceaſed from ſpirituall motions and actions, their veſſels are empty, their lamps going out, and themſelves laid down to ſleep. How dull and heavy are their ſpirituall ſenſes grown for want of holy exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? how liſtleſſe and liveleſſe are their Spirits?</p>
               <p>Oh then, 'tis high time, that all the faithfull ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt, ſhould fall afreſh upon their Maſters work with double diligence; to redeem that time which ſtole away while they ſlept, and can never be recalled. And indeed Chriſtians, of all
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170191:56"/>the men i'th world, ſhould not loſe time, who have the beſt and moſt imployment. Oh then, out of hand, take up that old thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving trade, of the practice of Piety in all Goſpel-duties, from a pure principle; as ever theſe would be found vvatching, at the coming of their Lord.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Converſe much with lively Saints, who are much upon their Spiritual Watch; their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will be very awakening, who are well avvakened. They will be knocking at the door of thy heart, feeling thy ſpiritual pulſe, and asking thee, if all be well within; they cannot but be jog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging at thy elbow, if thou keep thy hands in thy boſome, and lie ſlumbring with folded arms: As iron ſharpneth iron, ſo doth the face of a man his friend. Watchful ſervants will be call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off the ſlumbring ones from
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170191:57"/>beds of ſecurity; they will be whetting up the dull and lazie ſpirits of others, who have a good edge upon their own. Amongſt ſluggiſh Chriſtians, 'tis a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand to one, you'l grow ſleepy too for company; Sluggards will infect one another with the ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Evill; they'l lay a Cuſhion for you to ſit dovvn by them, and take your fill of this falſe reſt: There's no ſpiritual noyſe amongſt them, nor heavenly nevves; no heart-awakening words: All's either finfull ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, or ſmooth words, huſhing one another aſleep with their ſoft language: Liveleſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are like dying coals, which deadden one another, till there be never a coal to warm at. Oh then, if thou wouldſt have a Watchfull ſpirit, in this ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring age, look after communion in ſpirit with the moſt quick, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170191:57"/>lively-ſpirited Saints; heavenly ſparks, that are ever flying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as to their proper Region; they will be warm, avvakening, enlivening company, (being well heated by the fire of the Spirit) for luke-warm, drowſie, liveleſſe Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be ever ſetting on work avvakening Graces, by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Spirit of Grace. Stir up the Graces of Chriſt that are moſt ſtirring;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6.</note> and they'l ſtir up thee, quicken thee, and ſet thee on fire, as ſparks blown up, &amp;c,</p>
               <p>As, 1. <hi>Lively Faith.</hi> This is the new Creatures eye, quicker then the Eagles, excellent at Watching. 'Tis the ſpiritual mans Secr, and the overſeer of his watchings and workings; If this active grace be at work, it will keep the heart awake: the Watch cannot fall down, whileſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170191:58"/>Faith is up. It's a very buſie grace, which will keep us from ſleeping, if it ſleep not. Faith will be daily improving avvake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Providences, quickening ordinances, melting mercies, ſearching tryals; It will be ever taking in, awakening conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the majeſtie of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, the mutabilitie of the Creature, of Mortalitie, Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp;c: It will be preſenting awakening manifeſtations of the unconceiveable love of God, the incomparable lovelineſſe of Chriſt, the admirable beauty of holineſſe, the unſpeakable bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe of Heaven; It will be looking out at the eye, to ſee the King in his beauty, liſtning at care, to heare that voyce, which his companions heare, waiting at heart to welcome his Spirit there: Faith is all life, full of Spirit, a quick Spring, which
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170191:58"/>will ſet all on motion; 'Twill ſet the whole man on work, and actuate every habit of grace; Its operations are full of effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and varietie; upward, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, outward, it has a large ſphere of activitie; Oh could we live the life of Faith at a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate, how lively ſhould we be, how watchfull?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Warme Love;</hi> It's all heart and heat, there's a flame in it, which will enliven and awaken the moſt drowſie and heavie heart; There's much life in love, much action in this affection; it's activitie will keepe thee from ſecuritie: Love is good at watching, it will ſit up long for the Beloved; It cannot reſt, till he reſt in his love upon it;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.17.</note> it would not ſleepe (with its good will) till it may lie in his boſom,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 127.2.</note> and there it may reſt ſafely and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170191:59"/>ſweetly, when he gives his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved ſleep. Love will wait and watch long, endure much; hard duty is eaſie to it, as <hi>Jacob's</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for <hi>Rachel:</hi> Love lyes with eyes and heart open too, as loath to ſhut out Chriſt at either. It will wait long and longingly, for a look of his eye, a kiſſe from his mouth, the breathings of his love. An heart toucht with Chriſts love, cannot reſt (as the needle touched with the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone) but when and where it ſhould. Love has a ſingle eye, and will watch well; 'tis clear, and quick as the Doves; it will ſpie out its Beloved,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.9.</note> and pierce his heart.</p>
               <p>Oh could we but love much, we ſhould watch much; and wait to meet our Beloved at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry turn,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.12.</note> in his garden, in his ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queting-houſe, in his vineyards, to give up our loves to him; Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170191:59"/>love will be early and late at work and watch for Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Holy Fear.</hi> It will keep ſtrict watch and ſtrong guard, for fear of ſurpriſall: It is a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and watchful grace, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to be taken at un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awares. It's ever attended with a godly jealouſie, which will marvellouſly prevent carnal ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. Indeed, they that have not this fear of God before their eyes, and upon their hearts, they'l cloze their eyes, ſtop their ears, harden their hearts, and grow careleſſe and ſecure, as the men of <hi>Laiſh,</hi> even till fearfulneſſe and trembling come upon them; and they (of all others) are in greateſt danger of the fear and the ſnare, who fear leaſt; the deepeſt fear-leſſe ſecurity, will bring on the heavieſt fearful ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity. Oh then let all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170191:60"/>of the Lord watch over their own hearts, leſt they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fear of the Almighty, and he leave them to a common, careleſſe, fearleſſe ſpirit, and they be inſenſibly overtaken with ſpiritual ſecurity:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12, 13.</note> Oh <hi>Sanctifie the Lord of hoſts himſelf, let him be your fear, let him be your dread, that you may neither fear their fear, nor be afraid.</hi> And indeed, the more full thine heart is poſſeſſed with a filial, reverential fear of that glorious and fearful Name, <hi>The Lord thy God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.58.</note> the leſſe wilt thou be diſquieted with falſe heart-tormenting Feares and Cares; <hi>Bleſſed is he that feareth alwayes;</hi> he will be alwayes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Watch, to the preventing of much ſin and ſorrow, ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring and wandring, ſenſuality and ſecurity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Heavenly Joy;</hi> 'Tis very enlivening and heart-awaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170191:60"/>Like that <hi>of the beſt wine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.9.</note> 
                  <hi>which goes down ſweetly, cauſing the lips of thoſe that are aſleep to ſpeak.</hi> Where the ſpirit can rejoyce comfortably in the Lord, there his work will go on merrily; his Watch will be kept chearfully; ſuch a ſoul can ſing in the wayes of the Lord, and upon his watch even at midnight (as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi>);<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 16.25.</note> Whereas an heavy heart drives heavily in all its watchings and workings. <hi>Job</hi>'s ſoon out of heart, and cryes, <hi>What a wearineſſe?</hi> and, <hi>Why ſhould I wait on the Lord any longer?</hi> Every Command is grievous, to one that is grieved in ſpirit; and every word and work (though eaſie) ſeems a burthen to one that is a burthen to himſelf: Now Spiritual Joy, is like <hi>aqua coeleſtis,</hi> it will recover a languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſwooning ſpirit. This refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wine, drunk out of the cup
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170191:61"/>of ſalvation, is full of quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirits, and will make a Chriſtian hearty, ſpiritfull and watchful: They that ſuck, and are ſatisfied with the breaſts of conſolation, as they are caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſweet and ſound ſleep in the arms of Chriſt, ſo they will caſt off ſinful, ſluggiſh ſecurity.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Let Watching and Prayer go hand in hand; and they will lend an helping hand to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; they are lively, lovely companions joyned together by Chriſts own hand, and would be linked together as with a chain of gold in every Chriſtians heart: Watching and prayer are mutually helpful and ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170191:61"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Watchfulneſſe helps to lift up, and keep up Prayer, as Aaron and Hur held up the hands of Moſes, <hi>Exod. 17.12.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>It helps us to opportunities of Prayer.</hi> A ſlumbring ſpirit loſes many ſeaſons of Prayer, ſleeps out ſweet breathing-times of ſupplication. Where there is deep ſpiritual ſleep, there's deep ſilence, a dumb ſpirit is there: The Sluggard is folding his hands to reſt, when he ſhould be lifting up his heart with his hands unto God in the Heavens: If we watch not, Satan will make a prey of our praying-times; the World will be ſteal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away our time and hearts too; Our praying times are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious times, our enemies envy them; and, of all times, will be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170191:62"/>interpoſing, when we are any thing diſpoſed this way; they'l loſe no time, to make us loſe our beſt times; and if they can but take us off the duty of the day, they get the day; Now a watchfull Spirit will keep time with God, (in whoſe hands all our time is) who ever ſayes Nay; It thinks much to loſe one meeting with him, he muſt not be put off, what ever is put by. Vigilancie helps much, as to conſtancie and frequencie in prayer; an awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened heart will cry with <hi>David</hi> morning, evening, and at noon; It will prevent the dawning of the Morning; and the Night watches: ſuch a Soul, only, can continue in prayer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.17. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.147.148.</note> and pray continually, that is continually upon its Watch.</p>
               <p>Beſides, as watchfulneſſe helps to find out time for prayer; ſo, <hi>to chuſe out the fitteſt;</hi> when we are moſt at leaſure for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170191:62"/>in the beſt poſture for prayer; As Jeſus Chriſt was much at faſting and prayer, (and beſt at it) ſo he watched ſeaſons and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecie for prayer;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark.</hi> 1.25.</note> Hee's early at it, and ſolitarie; And as he counſels us to pray daily, ſo he cautions us to pray duly, ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſecretly;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>But thou, when thou prayeſt, enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut thy door, pray to thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret,</hi> &amp;c: We ſhould have nothing elſe to doe, when we have to do with God in prayer, Tis work enough alone; and he loves to have us much alone at this work; A man that is wiſe for his Soul, will watch a finding time, in all his ſeekings; and ſpeak moſt to the Lord, when ther's moſt hopes, he will be ſpoke with,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.6.</note> and he ſhall ſpeed beſt.</p>
               <p>Now a ſleepie heart is for any time, or no time; 'Tis apt to put
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170191:63"/>God off with the leaſt and laſt; when it's Spirit's low, ſtrength ſpent, affections earthly; when all out of frame, no help at it, no heart to it, no time for it; He nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther looks for Gods Spirit in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, nor at his own; And thus the Lord of all muſt be ſerved with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nything, or nothing by a ſloathful ſervant; whereas a vigilant ſoul watches Golden-Goſpel-ſeaſons, when it may offer up incenſe in Golden cenſers. When the heart's ful (as the Clouds) then to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it out; when 'tis as a bottle of new Wine wanting vent; then to ſpeak that it may be refreſhed (as <hi>Elihu</hi> did) when the Spirit moves,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 32.18, 19, 20.</note> when the heart is fixed, when the affections are warme, when moſt retired and inward. Theſe are the heavenly breathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing times with the awakened Virgins, for this holy exerciſe. Theſe are the living lively Saints
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170191:63"/>dayes for pure Spiritual recre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; theſe are their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary times on earth, upon which they pray down more then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary bleſſings from Heaven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Watchfullneſse helps us to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie in prayer:</hi> A watchfull Soul is good at holding out with Gods, ſits up with him &amp; for him.</p>
               <p>It will not keepe ſilence, while God is ſilent; It can take no reſt, and will give the Lord no reſt, till he heare in Heaven, and ſpeak to its heart; Take an awakened heart upon deep con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and how mightily will it cry unto the Lord, ſaying, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, awake, heare me ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and, How long Lord! 'Tis in great haſte now,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 40.1. <hi>Hebr.</hi>
                  </note> for an anſwer from Heaven; and the more haſte the better ſpeed in this ſenſe: Now it cannot but wait in wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, pray with a prayer;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.14.17. <hi>Gr.</hi>
                  </note> cry all the day: While its watch is up,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170191:64"/>its ſoul is lift up, that God would rejoyce the ſoul of his ſervant:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 86.3.4.</note> Its hard at work within at this heart-duty.</p>
               <p>Now a ſlumbring ſpirit has ſoon done; ſhorteſt prayers are ſweeteſt to it. It cares not for awakening the Lord, leſt he ſhould awaken it; It would be let alone, and therefore 'twill let him alone; it likes well to give the Lord reſt and it ſelf too: A ſleepy heart cannot <hi>lift up the hands that hang down,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knees.</hi> 'Tis the awakened Soul which ſtretcheth forth the hand towards God, whoſe eyes fail with looking up; that wra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles with him, as for life, (<hi>Jacob</hi>-like) and will not let him go without a bleſſing. Now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity does much with God in prayer;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.1.7.8.82. Gr.</note> 
                  <hi>Will not God avenge his Elect, that cry unto him day and night; I tell you,</hi> ſayes Chriſt,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170191:64"/>(who knevv his Fathers heart, coming from his boſome) <hi>he will Speedily;</hi> aſſoon as may be: Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer, though long at it, loſes no time; life and length in this duty will carry it at laſt: It will not be put off, not away till it has got an alms; it has got the skill on't, and will not leave knocking, till the door be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; It will have its will of God, (as one may ſay) becauſe it would have nothing but what God will. What a great word was that from Chriſt to great faith and fervency in prayer: <hi>Be it unto thee, as thou wilt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 15 28. <hi>Gr.</hi>
                  </note> Shee could wiſh no more, and ſhe muſt have no leſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Watchfullneſs helps to idoneitie in prayer;</hi> Awakened hearts are readieſt to cry to the Lord, and to heare him ſpeak: 'Its an inſtrument in tune to pray with; ſuch an heart God himſelf has
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170191:65"/>prepared for himſelf, and he will cauſe his eare to heare, and prepare of his goodneſſe for it too; A Chriſtian upon his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall watch may ſay, <hi>My heart is readie, O God, my heart is readie;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 10.17.</note>'Tis an excellent frame of ſpirit for any ſpiritual duty, at any time.</p>
               <p>A ſlumbring Spirit is moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for holy ſtrivings and ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings with God; none more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to this ſtirring duty, or leſſe affected at it; When the heart is aſleep, prayer is but a dream; 'Tis phanſie works then, not faith; there's onely a ſound of words, no ſound words; All's <hi>but as ſounding braſse, or as a tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Cymball;</hi> it makes no muſick in Gods eare; All's to ſeeke in ſuch a heart, faith, deſires, hope &amp;c, it's ever at a loſſe; All's dead in a manner here, there's no breathing almoſt; Oh what a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170191:65"/>diſtempered, diſtracted ſpirit in prayer, where no watch is kept? what averſions from it, what di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions in it? How will the heart wander up and down, and give us the ſlip, if not watched? What ſtrange withdrawings, &amp; miſgivings of ſpirit, when we draw nigh to give up our hearts to the Lord? what a croud of confuſed thoughts in a ſleepie heart? weak and low graces are ſoon loſt in it; 'Tis ſuch a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row-fare for Sctans ſuggeſtions, that Chriſt has little or no room there; Now a watchfull Spirit will be ſure to ſhut the door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all theſe: that Chriſt may have all to himſelf, the heart muſt be kept, as a cloſet for him and the Soul to meet in.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In point of Receptivitie; watchfullneſſe puts a Soul into a capacitie to take in much from God by prayer: as to be much
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170191:66"/>at it, and to do much in it, ſo to get much by it; God will be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver giving to that Soul, that gives it ſelf unto prayer. A man that is all prayer (to allude to the expreſſion in the original) whoſe heart is all upon it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 109 4. <hi>Heb.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Davids,</hi> muſt needs be a getting growing man; hee, drives ſo thriving a trade thoroughly; Now there's none better at it, then awakened hearts, and ſo none fitter to wait.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>For ſupply and ſupport in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er;</hi> Spiritual ſupplications can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be carryed on but by the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Spirit of Jeſus-Chriſt, which <hi>Paul</hi> reckoned ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably on;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.19.</note> theſe ſweet ſpices will not flow without the breathings of the holy Ghoſt; It's well known to an awakened Soul, that we cannot think a good thought of our ſelves; 'Tis onely Gods good Spirit, that can teach us
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170191:66"/>to indite good matter;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 45.1. <hi>Hebr.</hi>
                  </note> his quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings make our Spirits as a living Spring, to buble up and boyle over in fervent prayer;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.6.</note> when he touches the lips with a living coale (as one of the Seraphims did the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi>) then our <hi>tongues will be like the pens of a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die writer.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>Gr.</hi>
                  </note> An experienced Chriſtian, when awake, feeles at his heart; he cannot help up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in prayer, and therefore he waites for the Spirit to help his infirmities, he knows not how to turn his hand or heart to the work, without an helping hand from Heaven at every turn; and therefore he waits and weeps for the Spirit to help him out, <hi>with ſighs and groans that cannot be uttered:</hi> and though he have no ſtrength of his own, yet he has power with God, having power from God.</p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170191:67"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>For ſucceſse and ſatisfaction after Prayer.</hi> He that watches unto prayer and in it, will wait for the return of prayer, day after day, as <hi>Noah</hi> did for the Dove, till it returned with an Olive leaf in its mouth: when he has <hi>ſowen in tears,</hi> he waits for the precious fruits of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual harveſt, till he <hi>reap in joy:</hi> he looks long and longingly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his prayers and tears with an open eye and heart; hee's ever and anon hearkening what the Lord will ſay, after all his ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, and pleading with him by a ſpirit of ſupplication; he muſt hear and feel at his heart, that God hears in heaven: when he has done praying, his faith is as buſie with God at his promiſes, as the Bee at flowers, and will not have done, till pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er comes home laden with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Thus poor beggars, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170191:67"/>have the skill of waiting in prayer, and after it, get a good living by it; 'tis a good ſtock, that brings in great ſtore of new and old; Now a ſlothfull ſpirit has no heart at all, to look after his prayers, that had no heart in them; they die in the birth, and are ſtill-born; how can he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect God ſhould hear thoſe prayers, which he ſcarce hears himſelf? They make no noyſe in heaven, and there can be no good newes of them on earth; they'l find Gods ear heavy, who find their hearts ſo; whereas a watchfull heart may reckon much of the incoms of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſhall have a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of them one day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170191:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Prayer helps to keep up our Watch; it cannot fall down, while Prayer is up with faith and ferven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.</head>
               <p n="1">1. It helps up a Chriſtians Watch, and keeps it up, as it brings in the Keeper of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, to help us to watch. The prayer of faith crys loud in his ears, and awakens him, to a waken us; it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes him (as for life) to quicken up our ſpirits to this ſpirituall Watch; It has power with God, and fetches power from him, to ſtrengthen weak hands and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knees,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31.</note> in this holy duty. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon the wings of faith, will fetch down Eagles wings in a promiſe, to mount up with, in this high and heavenly exerciſe, of waiting on the Lord, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170191:68"/>watching for him; Watching is hard work, and long duty; and alas, we are ſoon tyred out in any thing of ſpiritual duty; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if any thing of difficulty in it, we are ready at every turn to lie down to reſt.</p>
               <p>Now lively prayer ſtirres up the Lord to ſtirre us up; It will ſet him awork at our hearts; and his heart-workings are heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awakenings; while we are knocking at the gates of Heaven, and jogging (as it were) of Chriſts elbow, by ſtirring and ſtrong cryes; his ſpirit will be knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the door of our hearts; and jogging our ſpirits, to keep them awake: Let a poor heart but cry in the Ears of the Lord, and it ſhall hear a voyce from heaven behind it, yea within it, ſaying, Ariſe my Love and come away, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170191:69"/>
               <p n="2">2. Prayer helps in watching,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 121.</note> as it engages the Lord to watch over our watchings, without whom all our watchings would be in vain; he keeps a ſtrict watch over his waiting ſervants day and night, for he neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps. Alas, we cannot keep our ſouls alive, nor our heart awake; but prayer takes the Lord into the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tower with us, and he ſets a guard upon our hearts, a watch before our lips, &amp;c. Hee's a tower of ſalvation to his people, and keeps them as in a garriſon by his own power,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> while they are upon his Watch, and at his Work. The Watch muſt needs be ſafely and ſweetly kept, where Jeſus Chriſt is Captain of the Guard; we ſhould be certainly ſurprized even upon our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Watch by thoſe ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170191:69"/>who are too high and too many for us. Were we not ſet upon the Rock that is higher then we,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 61.2.</note> that is higher then they, the Rock Chriſt: we ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as naked men, even at our arms, did not the <hi>Captain of our Salvation</hi> watch with us, and over us; now Chriſts waiting-ſervants are ever calling him in, by the <hi>prayer of Faith,</hi> to keep up their Watch for them, by wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching over them;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Sam. <hi>28.2.</hi> Achiſh to David.</note> their effectual prayers lay ſtrong hands upon him, to keep him with them, as the Keeper of their heads and hearts for ever.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Prayer helps a Chriſtian to Watch, as it brings him in to commune with God, who is <hi>glorious in holineſſe, fearful in praiſes, doing wonders.</hi> When a poor ſilly, ſinful Wretch comes to preſent himſelf before the <hi>Holy One, who is of purer eyes then
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170191:70"/>to behold iniquity.</hi> How will the ſerious thoughts of the tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent majeſty, and reſplendent purity of <hi>Jehovah</hi> awaken him? <hi>Will not his excellency make</hi> him <hi>afraid,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 13.11.</note> 
                  <hi>and his dread fall upon</hi> him? When <hi>Abraham</hi> drew near to commune with the Lord, what awakened poſture does he appear in?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 18 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Behold</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>I have taken upon me to ſpeak to the Lord, who am but duſt and aſhes. Oh let not the Lord be angry,</hi> &amp;c. When a Child of God finds in his heart to plead with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Heaven, he firſt pleades with himſelf in theſe or the like words;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Wherewithall ſhall I appear before the Lord, or bow my ſelf to the mighty God of Jacob?</hi> Awake, O my ſoul, awake, and offer not the dead, the lame and the ſick in ſacrifice to the living God: Hee's <hi>a great King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and his Name is dreadfull:</hi> And as a gracious
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170191:70"/>ſpirit communes with its own heart, before it commune with him that tryes the heart; ſo the Lord communes with it in and after prayer: now the voyce of the Lord is a glorious voyce, which ſhakes the Cedars; and will it not then ſhake a bruiſed reed, and make it tremble at his Word? A broken heart that can ſpeak its mind freely and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to the Lord, and hears him ſpeaking home to his heart, muſt needs be effectually awakened; ſuch heavenly entercourſe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by a ſpirit of prayer, will keep up a Chriſtians ſpirit in a watchful frame, till it go up to God that gave it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Prayer helps exceedingly at this heart-watch, as it is mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellouſly heart-affecting: In fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayer, how does the ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heart melt in godly ſorrow, (as ſnow before the Sun, or wax
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170191:71"/>by the fire?) mourning over the Lord and after him? how does the thirſting ſoul pant and breathe, and break with longings after the living God, as a thirſty land? how are the affections carried up towards heaven, in a pure flame of Divine life and love, aſcending as pillars of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed ſmoke? And will not ſuch unconceiveable Soul-ſtirrings &amp; ſtrugglings as theſe awaken the heart? Sure there is a mighty ſpirit of activity goes forth in this Saints-exerciſe, when performed in the power of the holy Spirit, which will prevent heart-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numming ſecurity; when a man of God wraſtles with the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty in his might as a Gyant refreſhed with Wine; what heart-raiſing and rowſing work muſt there needs be (think ye)? 'Tis too buſie a time this, to ſleep in, when an immortal ſoul
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170191:71"/>is working, as for life, with the ever-living God, about the things of Eternity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A double ground in the Text, why we ſhould double our duty in Watching and Praying.</head>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe we are expoſed to temptation, if we do not Watch and Pray; For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We provoke the Lord to tempt us, while we tempt him by neglect of theſe Goſpel-Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, of his own appointment; as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To lead us into temptation, when we will not follow the leading and guidance of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit and Word: 'Tis that which Jeſus Chriſt, in tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to our weak, wandring ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, would have daily upon our hearts in prayer, to beſeech our
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170191:72"/>Father, not to lead us into tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, as the Spirit of truth teſtifies, that God <hi>cannot be tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to evill, neither tempteth he any man.</hi> He is infinitely holy and righteous, and cannot tempt any to ſin and unrighteouſneſſe: He is the chief good, and cannot lead any into any evil temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or temptation to evil: And he is unchangeably and eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly holy, and cannot poſſibly be tempted to unholineſſe: the juſt Lord will, can do, nothing that is unjuſt, no iniquity.</p>
               <p>Yet the Lord may be ſaid in his own ſenſe, to lead us into temptation, for himſelf hath ſaid it. As,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By way of Probation.</hi> When he tryes us like gold i'th fire, as he did <hi>Job.</hi> When he leads us into the Wilderneſſe, to prove us, as he did <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old; when
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170191:72"/>we fall into the hands of God, as <hi>David</hi> and his Servants did:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.2</note> And though we are to <hi>account it all joy when we fall into manifold temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for as the temptations and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt abound in us,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo our conſolations alſo will abound by Chriſt;</hi> 'tis his peculiar method (with which his ſecret ones are well acquainted) to bring good out of evill, and ſweet out of bitter, yet it is upon the account of his ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy with us in ſufferings, and ſanctifying them to us, by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the ſpirituall exerciſe of watching and prayer, while we are exerciſed therewith; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, as afflictions are never joyous in themſelves, ſo they will be ever grievous to thoſe, who have grieved the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; by laying aſide their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual watchfulneſſe and prayer: Thoſe ſufferings muſt needes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of vexation, and perplexitie,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170191:73"/>which find us under preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſecuritie; for,</p>
               <p>Firſt, what bitterneſſe will it be to the ſoul, when awakened in a day of adverſity, that it ſlept and ſlumbred out it's dayes of proſperitie; that which was then a bed of eaſe to the fleſh, will be now a bed of thorns to the Spirit. There cannot chuſe but be much heart-aking, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heart-awakening tryals, to all ſlumbring Virgins; and that is the pain of all paines, the ſharpeſt ſting in ſufferings; ſad thoughts of ſinfull ſlumbrings will break ones ſleep; falſe reſts will fearfully diſquiet us, when we find them out, or they us in, the day of calamity. Affliction will be a root of bitterneſſe bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gall and wormwood at ſuch a time; oh what an heavie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then has the careleſſe neglect of watching and praying been, to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170191:73"/>ſome ſlumbring Chriſtians in our dayes, who have lived at eaſe in Zion, while ſhe has been in pain travelling to be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? How have they <hi>mourned like Doves, and chattered as a Crane, or Swallow,</hi> for want of that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace and ſupplication, which they had ſo long reſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and ſo much extinguiſhed, under a ſpirituall Lethargie? how have their hearts been rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to dye within them, like <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals,</hi> for want of life in, and love to, thoſe holy duties, wherein ſometimes they had been lively and full of affection? How will the hearts of all the ſlumbring Virgins ſmite them one day, when diſtreſſe ſhall come upon them, as ſorrow upon a woman in travell? will they not then weep out their ſleepy eyes, and ſigh out their ſluggiſh ſpirits, crying, Ah we fools, that had
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170191:74"/>a price in our hands, and no hearts to uſe it? We have loſt many a good day, trifling out choyce breathing times, in the ſight of the Sun; and now the night is come upon us, and we cannot work: Alas, alas, for thoſe daies of the Son of Man;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 29.2, 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Oh that it were with us as in the moneths of old, when the candle of the Lord ſhined upon our heads, &amp;c.</hi> What ſlothful ſervants have we been, hiding our Maſters Talents in a napkin, when we ſhould have <hi>miniſtred one to another,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>as good Stewards of the manifold Grace of God?</hi> And now the ruſt of them witneſſes againſt us, as the worldlings gold and ſilver. We have ſhut our ears and hearts againſt the Lord and his good Word, and now the Word of the Lord is againſt us. We have ſlighted the ſweet counſell and comforts of the holy Spirit,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170191:74"/>and now we feel its ſharp Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions: We would not hear the checks of Conſcience, and now we muſt hear its chidings. Oh the ſting and the ſmart of a ſelf-condemning Conſeience, when it is once awakened out of ſelf-pleaſing, and ſelf-eaſing ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, by the ſcourging rod of the Almighty.</p>
               <p>Secondly, what Averſeneſſe and frowardneſſe, will fill thy Spirit in ſad houres, who haſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſlipt and ſlept out ſo many good ones? When thou feeleſt thy ſufferings weightie, and thy ſhoulders weake; thy preſſures great and thy patience ſmall, thy body languiſhing, thy ſoul faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, thy faith failing; How will thy Spirit be diſtempered; thy peace diſturbed, thy heart will be readie to <hi>fret againſt the Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.3.</note> thou'l be angrie as <hi>Jonah, even to the death;</hi> to ſee death looking
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170191:75"/>thee in the face, when thou laſt looked for it, and the evill day, neereſt, when thou puts it far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt from thee; And now thy ſlumbrings and wandrings will be ſet in order before thee, and thou haſt neither ſet thy houſe or heart in order before the Lord; and now the Judge ſtandeth at the door, to call thee to an account and thou haſt not made up thy reckonings for many a day; thy time miſſpent, thy ſtock ſpent; thy experiences loſt, thy evidence to ſeek; Oh how diſcontented will thy diſappointed heart be at ſuch a day? Thou haſt long neglected the ruling of thy own ſpirit, and now 'twill be too unruly for thee, as a wild bull in a net; how apt wilt thou be to kick againſt the pricks (<hi>Ephraim</hi>-like) as a bullock unaccuſtomed to the yoke. An heart not watcht over, will be much out of frame
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170191:75"/>for doing well, much more for ſuffering. When the weight of affliction falls upon a lazy, lame ſpirit; what haltings will be diſcovered, and uneaven car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage under the rod?</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>By way of Permiſsion.</hi> As the Lord may be ſaid to lead us into temptation by way of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, when he takes us into his own hand; ſo by way of Conceſſion, when he takes off his own hand; and ſuffers Satan to put forth his hand againſt us. 'Tis true, the evil one is alwaies limited by the Holy One, that he cannot do his worſt; or elſe he would play the devil indeed: he's under Divine reſtraint (and in a priſon, as it were) when moſt at liberty; this ſtrong man armed is reſerved in chains, by a ſtronger then he; Yet his heart is ſet upon the ſervants of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 1.8. <hi>Hebr.</hi>
                  </note> (as 'twas upon <hi>Job</hi>) with as much
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170191:76"/>ill will, as it can hold, (though through mercy, he cannot have his will on them) The roaring Lyon gapes with open mouth to ſwallow them up. How earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did he deſire to ſift the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſt?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31. <hi>Gr.</hi>
                  </note> he was greedy of ſuch a prey as this: and if the Lord did not put an hook in the noſtrils of this Leviathan, what a piercing Serpent would he be? How ready was the evil ſpirit to offer his ſervice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.1.</note> to be a lying ſpirit in the mouth of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets? he would fain be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 22.22.</note> that he might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying. Now if we neglect our ſpiritual Watch, we grieve the Spirit, and tempt him to leave us to the temptations of the evil ſpirit, who will be ever grieving and vexing our ſpirits, and doing us all the miſchief he can, and 'tis much he can do with Gods leave: if the Lord
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170191:76"/>take away the hedge, this wild Boor will be in upon us, and root up all.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We tempt the Lord to tempt us, when we give over watching and praying, by lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us in temptation, as by leading us into it; and that's a very Sad Caſe.</p>
               <p>As, 1. By withdrawing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his holy Spirit from us, when we are under tryals: And this muſt needs be a dark time, when God covers us with a cloud in his anger, and covers himſelf as with a cloud too. What a terrible Eclipſe will that be, when the light of his Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is withheld, in a day of darkneſſe and gloomineſſe? This indeed is the burthen of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and lyes heavieſt upon honeſt hearts: This is plain to ſee in the ſeverall perplexed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and diſtreſſed conditions of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170191:77"/>
                  <hi>Job,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 13.21. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 88.14. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 13.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Heman, David,</hi> &amp;c. under variety of afflictions and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. The hiding of Gods face was the foreſt trouble, the ſaddeſt tryal; this ſtruck deepeſt into their hearts, and made their faces gather paleneſſe: how were their ſpirits drunk up with the <hi>terrours of the Almighty?</hi> Now 'tis moſt righteous with the Lord, to leave us in a day of adverſity, when we leave him in dayes of proſperity; to leave us at a loſſe in our ſtraits, when we leave and loſe him in liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. He will withdraw from us, when evill drawes near, if we have withdrawn and wandred from him, when he drew near to do us good: He will turn his back upon them in times of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity, who have given him the back and not the face in times of tranquillity.</p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170191:77"/>
               <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 81.11, 12.</note> By delivering us up to our ſelves and our own ſpirits. When Gods people would have none of Him, <hi>He gave them up to their own hearts luſts;</hi> they would not own the Lord, and be his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; and he leaves them to be ſlaves to their own luſts, lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it over them. Ah, when a people grow weary of God, have done with him as to Watching in prayer, and let him alone, coming ſeldom at him; hee'l be a ſtranger to them, and leave them alone, as he did <hi>Ephraim:</hi> Hee's joyned to Idols,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17, 18.</note> let him alone, (ſayes God) he will not joyn himſelf to the Lord, and the Lord will have nothing to do with him, but leave him to himſelf, and to his Idols; and now all goes ill with poor <hi>Ephraim:</hi> his drink is ſowr, or is gone, (as in the Hebrew) all is gone, when God is gone; and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170191:78"/>he commits whoredome conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually; all ſowres on his hands, and in his heart too. Ah, when we ſlight the Lord, and ſlumber in his ſight; he will let us ſlip out of his hands, and then (as a bowl falling out of the hand, down a ſteep hill) we follow the Byaſſe of our own corrupt hearts, and run headlong without ſtop or ſtay Hell-ward. 'Tis not to ſay, How fearfully and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully the beſt of men will leave the Lord and loſe themſelves, when left to themſelves? We have remarkable proofs of this in thoſe precious ſervants of the Lord of old, <hi>David, Solomon, Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c: they made themſelves vile; yea even as beaſts before him, when they were left to themſelves? And we have many lamentable inſtances in our dayes, of ſuch, who looked like the ſheep coming up from the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170191:78"/>waſhing, clean eſcaped from the pollutions of the world, yet have <hi>turned like the dogge to the vomit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, 21, 22.</note> 
                  <hi>and as the ſow that was waſhed to the wallowing in the mire;</hi> Would it ever have entred into their own hearts that they ſhould ever have ſo fowlie defiled their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which ſeemed to have been waſhed ſo ſaire in the blood of the Lamb?<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 8.13.</note> would they not have ſaid (with <hi>Hazael</hi>) <hi>Are we as dogs, that we ſhould do ſuch things?</hi> Oh yes, when a people are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered up to themſelves, they will be readie to ſay with thoſe, (of whom the Lord complaines) <hi>We are delivered up to do all theſe abominations;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.10.</note> If we leave the Lord and his watch and work; we tempt him to leave us in temptation to our own hearts; and then that plague will be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>xod.</hi> 9.14.</note> (which fell upon the heart of <hi>Pharoah</hi>) which was
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170191:79"/>worſe to him then all the plagues of Egypt; and we ſhall even harden our ſelves againſt the Lord.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We tempt the Divell, that tempter, to tempt us, when we give over watching and praying; He watches our ſlumbrings, and lyes at catch for us, when he may take us napping; when we have a mind to fall aſleepe upon a bed of carnal ſecuritie, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil will make our bed for us, and lie down ſoftly by us too: when we give over Gods work, we are out of his way; and lie ſleeping in Satans walks, and that as drie Tinder to his fierie darts: And there come but a ſpark from Hell, and fall upon our hearts, it takes preſently: when we put out the light and fall to ſleep, we give him roome and time for his works of darkneſſe; he drives his wicked trade moſt and beſt
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170191:79"/>i'th dark;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 24.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>The eye of</hi> this Arch-<hi>thiefe waiteth for the twilight, when no eyes may ſee him,</hi> he looks at us moſt with his envious eyes, when our eyes are ſhut, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of ſpiritual darkneſſe are upon us; and how eaſily may he ſteale away our hearts, and the heavenly treaſure out of them, at ſuch a time as <hi>David</hi> did <hi>Sauls</hi> ſpeare from his bolſter,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.12.</note> when a deep ſleep was upon him. And indeed this thief in the night (to allude ſtill to that place in <hi>Job</hi>) would rob us of all our Jewels, when a dead ſleep is upon us, did not our faithfull keeper watch him, and watch over us: Oh what danger are we in every houre, to become a prey to this roaring Lyon, while we lie ſleeping at his feet? the fowles of the ayr have the greateſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage againſt us that may be, whilſt we lie as ſilly doves,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170191:80"/>heartleſſe and ſpiritleſſe before them. And is not this a very foule buſineſſe, to ſet the Divel on work to do us miſchief, who will hurt us and hinder us all he can, and that by neglecting our Maſters buſineſſe, who has done us good and no evill, all our dayes.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We tempt our own luſts to tempt us, when we lay aſide our ſpiritual watch; we entice them to entice and allure us; And indeed here lies the great temptation within our own hearts,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Every man is tempted, when he is drawn away of his own luſt, and entiſed, and ſin when conceived bringeth forth death:</hi> The privy ſore in the heart, the deadiy wound; the womb that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives luſt, ſin, death. Here the Devil layes his train ef powder, and were there no fire of luſt there, he could never blow us
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170191:80"/>up; temptations without could take no hold, if there were no corruption within; Satan ſet up on Jeſus Chriſt with varietie of temptations,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.30.</note> but could find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in him, and ſo could do nothing againſt him: The Prince of this world, was ever warring againſt the Prince of peace, but had no power againſt him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had no party within him. Nay the ſubtle Serpent with all his power and policie could not prevaile at all, no not, once againſt the weakeſt, ſimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt Saint, if ſin did not take his part. Tis the partie within be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayes us; Tis the worſt enemy, that within; it opens the door to our enemies without, yea to the worſt of them, or they could not get within us; Now when we are fallen into a dead ſleep, and have loſt the life of prayer; our luſts will ſwarme about us, as
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170191:81"/>flies about a dead carcaſe: Sinnes not watched over, will get head and heart whilſt we indulge our ſelves ſaying, Soul, take thine eaſe; we pamper our ſins and make proviſion for the fleſh, to fulfill the luſts thereof! Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al watching and prayer will ſtarve our luſts, eaſe out their very hearts, but carnal ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings and ſleepings feed them.</p>
               <p>While prayer is kept up in power, ſin is kept down and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpowered; if our ſinnes do not ſtop our mouths, nor ſtraiten our hearts in prayer; our prayers will cry them down, and ſtob them at heart, when our hearts are lift up powerfully in prayer; our heart-ſinnes, as pride, paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, unbeliefe, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> will come down wonderfully (as the <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites</hi> fell, while <hi>Moſes</hi> lift up his hands) oh while we continue wreſtling with God by fervent
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170191:81"/>prayer; we may wreſtle with <hi>ſpirituall wickedneſſes in high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and that to victory; our ſouls ſhall <hi>tread down ſtrength</hi> (to uſe <hi>Deborahs</hi> expreſſion in her try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Song),<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.21.</note> while they are lift up, and poured out in prayer, for the Help that is laid upon that One that is mighty. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, if our hands be let down, and our hearts fall, our corruptions will get up and carry it againſt us with a ſtrong hand: if we be not watchful and prayerful, ſin will grow exceeding ſinful:<note place="margin">Job <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>If we reſtrain prayer before God, our mouths will utter iniquity;</hi> (as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaid to <hi>Job</hi>) who ſeems to plead thus with him; How comeſt thou to be ſo diſtempered in ſpirit, ſo vain and diſtracted in ſpeech; if prayer were not reſtrained? Fervent, conſtant prayer would bring the heart
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170191:82"/>into a good tune and temper, and keep it ſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When we neglect our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Watch, we lie naked to temptations without, as to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions within; the creatures are full of ſnares, and we ſhall be catched in them at every turn, if a ſpirit of ſlumber be upon us. The love of the world is connatural to us, bred i'th bone, moſt ſuitable to fleſh and blood; our hearts hang down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and move towards earth and earthly things, as a ſtone to the Center; and 'tis impoſſible to keep them up without watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer. Indeed, while we keep cloſe to God by faith in prayer, we keep him cloſe to us; and then the world may not interpoſe, muſt not be cloſed with,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.4.</note> upon any terms; <hi>For grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is he that is in us, then he that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170191:82"/>is in the world.</hi> And while we Watch and Pray, our ſpirituall weapons will be <hi>mighty through God, to bring down all the ſtrong holds of the god of this world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luther</hi> was one of the moſt watchfull ſpirits in prayer, (we read of) and he ſpeaks of one of the higheſt experiences that we ſhall meet with; That he was never tempted to Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; there was no fiſhing for his ſpirit with golden baits, which was carried ſo high above the world in Faith and Prayer.</p>
               <p>But alas, Chriſtians now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes find the world a very great temptation, a world of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in it. How is the Moon got up to the heart; in this our age, that uſed to be under foot,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.2.</note> to ſuch as are clothed with the Sun? Oh what hoarding up trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure on earth, by ſuch as ſeemed to be heires of Heaven, as if their
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170191:83"/>Heaven were upon earth, and their hearts too.</p>
               <p>How unbecoming is this to thoſe that are born from above, to live beneath themſelves: that ever ſo noble ſpirits of the blood-Royall, ſhould be ſo embaſed; &amp; precious Sons and Daughters of <hi>Zion,</hi> who were comparable to fine Gold, ſhould (in this ſenſe) become as earthen pitchers? How contrary is this to thoſe heavenly principles of faith and love, which ſhould carry us as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Eagles wings above the world towards heaven? Oh where is the love of the Father, where there is ſo much love of the World? Have you ever taſted of the powers of the World to come, who are thus brought under the power of the Creature? What, ſhall the Children of the Kingdom look no further, live no higher then the Kingdoms of this World?
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170191:83"/>What, called out of the World, and at the Worlds call too? Theſe things could never be, if watching and prayer had been kept up all this while, with life and power; 'Twere not poſſible the World ſhould ſteale upon the hearts of Gods people thus, and ſteale them away too, were they not aſleep: Now when prayer's down, and the World up, what a downfall will there bee? <hi>They fall into temptation and aſnare, and into many hurtfull and fooliſh luſts, which drown men in perdition,</hi> Oh what a root of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſprings up, where the World takes deep root; how do they <hi>pierce themſelves thorough with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſorrowes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6 9, 10.</note> and choak the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſeeds of grace with theſe thornes: and when the heart is overcharged with the inordinate love of this preſent World; This ſoul-benumming Lethargie of
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170191:84"/>carnal ſecuritie will overſpread it, that we ſhall not feele this ſin within us, when it is even all over us; what ſenſe can we have of our living by Senſe, whiles Faith lies dead? The love of the World will grow inſenſibly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, if it can but lull us aſleep in its Armes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, becauſe we ſhall be indiſpoſed to make any oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in an hour of temptation, if we do not Watch and Pray; our temptations will grow ſtronger, and we weaker in Spirit every day then other; they will be as Gyants, and we as Graſhoppers, (to uſe the expreſſion of the Spies). And alas, as we are ſo is our ſtrength (as <hi>Gideon</hi> ſaid of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>), at the beſt but weakneſſe; and our ſpirituall enemies will gather up their ſtrength to take the advantage of us, when and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170191:84"/>where we are weakeſt; How ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily may they make a prey of us, coming upon us vvhen vve are ſore, as <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Males?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.25.</note> eſpecially if vve conſider.</p>
               <p n="10">10. That the Strength of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> has ſecretly vvithdravvn himſelf from his people, vvhile their hearts have been aſleep,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 14 9.</note> and novv their defence is departed from them, and they are as bread to the devouring mouth of the hungry Lyon, vvho never had a better ſtomack to them. <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Judg.</hi> 16 19.20.</note> vvho vvas ſo ſtrong in the ſtrength of God, vvas as vveak as another man, vvhen the Lord departed from him; the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines may novv bind him as they pleaſe, put out his eyes, and make him grind it'h Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe! Ah, ſince the Lord has turned his back upon a backſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generation; hovv are the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170191:85"/>ſtrong become as bow, and they that had the excellencie of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and ſtrength are as unſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the water; how miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly are they ſwallowed up of temptations on every ſide? how eaſily lead captive by their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions at every turne; And though they ſhake themſelves ſomtimes (as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did) and think to reſiſt them as at other times; alas, they cannot do it, for their ſtrength is departed from them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Lord hath left them to themſelves, who have laid him aſide and left off watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer; Now what can ſuch naked men do in an hour of Temptation, when they meet with the ſtrong man armed? muſt they not needs be ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, like <hi>Saul</hi> in the day of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, when he was left to his own Spirit,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.20.</note> and had no ſtrength
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170191:85"/>in him? What a pittifull for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorn creature is that man whom God has given over, and given up to himſelf; even like a lamb in a large place,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.16.</note> as back-ſliding <hi>Iſrael;</hi> what more deſtitute, and diſtreſſed, where no Shepherd, no flock? how will it wander and loſe it ſelf? The beſt of men in ſuch a caſe are expoſed to the worſt of evills; when <hi>David</hi> a man after Gods own heart, was truſted but a while with his own heart, how ſhamfully it deceived him and defiled him? who would ever have thought that murthers and adulteries ſhould have proceeded out of ſuch a heart as his? When <hi>Solomon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Neh.</hi> 13 26.</note> who was ſo beloved of his God, was given up to himſelf; how ſtrangely was his heart changed within him, and turned from the Lord God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170191:86"/>to him twice, even to ſtrange gods,<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.8.</note> and ſtrange wives. The wiſeſt of men, when left to his own wiſdom, appears as one of the fools in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther does his ſhame go? And good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.31.</note> when the Lord left him, to try him, to know all that was in his heart; what pride of heart does he diſcover; (though he had been ſo lately and ſo deeply humbled)? And though the Lord had newly emptied all worldly glory before his eyes;<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.13.</note> Yet he could not keep his eyes and heart off of the houſe of his precious things, &amp;c. but glories in ſhewing all the treaſures were faund there: when he ſhould have glorified God, and ſhewed forth his wonders, in bringing the Sun of his life back,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38.</note> and the ſhadow upon the dyal of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170191:86"/>
               <p>Yea bleſſed <hi>Peter,</hi> an holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, when he truſted to his own ſtrength, and boldly profeſſed above the rate of the reſt of the Diſciples,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 26 33, 35.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Though all men ſhall be offended becauſe of thee, yet will I never be offended; and though I ſhould die with thee, yet will I not deny thee.</hi> When Chriſt truſts him with himſelf and his own ſtrength, (but for a little ſeaſon) how fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he ſhews his weakneſſe, and ſhames himſelf; and very ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully offends him more then they all, by being ſo ſhamefully of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended becauſe of him; denying before them all, that he knew his Maſter, upon the word of a damſel that ſaid, <hi>Thou waſt with Jeſus.</hi> And the Holy Ghoſt ſets a brand of Cowardize upon this ſelf-confiding Champion; lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this upon record to all Ages (to ſhake and ſhame all the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170191:87"/>Lords people out of themſelves), that when another Maid ſaid, <hi>This fellow was with Jeſus, he denyed with an oath,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ver.</hi> 71.</note> 
                  <hi>I know not the man.</hi> Would any of the Diſciples have ever believed ſuch a thing as this of <hi>Peter?</hi> or he, of himſelf? that a curſed oath ſhould have ever been found within his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lips, and that to deny his Lord and Maſter with thoſe lips that had ſo oft bleſſed him; that he ſhould ſo deſperately diſown him with his mouth, whom he owned, honoured, and loved ſo dearly at his heart.</p>
               <p>Oh how have the mighty fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, how have the mighty fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len! when they have been left to themſelves, and have fallen into their own hands. Such remarkable examples as theſe taken into our ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may happily (if the Lord ſtrike in with them) awaken
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170191:87"/>ſome ſleepy hearts from a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſelf-full ſecurity, to a religious watchfull jealouſie; that they who think they ſtand, may take heed leſt they fall; as certainly they ſhall, (though they ſeem to be pillars, as <hi>Peter</hi> did) if they ſtand upon their own leggs, and not upon his, that are <hi>as Pillars of Marble ſet upon ſockets of fine gold.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.15.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Upon this double Account, that they are ſo expoſed to Temptation, and ſo indiſpoſed to Oppoſition, who do no Watch and Pray: Let me call for double diligence in the Name of the Lord, to this double Duty.</head>
               <head type="sub">Firſt, Double your Watch; Oh watch, watch,</head>
               <p n="1">1. Over your own Hearts;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note> for they are moſt deceitfull, and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170191:88"/>the Deceiver lyes moſt at catch there: the ſubtle Serpent he knowes where our guile lyes, which he would willingly make uſe of, to beguile us with. 'Tis his Commiſſion, onely to bruiſe the heel;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note> but 'tis his covetous ambition to break into the heart. How he watches day and night, works without wearineſſe, and windes about every way, to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize this Royall Fort of the King of Glory? if he carry that, he commands all, and will lead us captive at his will; if he can but get his head into our hearts, and keep his hand upon this great wheel, he has his hearts deſire, and will turn all about with it. Oh therefore lay to heart that bleſſed Counſell of our great heart-keeper;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Keep thy heart above all keeping,</hi> (ſo the Hebrew has it) <hi>for out of it are the iſsues of life.</hi> 'Tis matter of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170191:88"/>life and death, this; 'Tis as much as thy life is worth, to watch the heart well; and not to watch it, is death. The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill knowes, if there be any good treaſure within thee, it is laid up in thine heart; and he would fain have the key of this Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, to rob thee of thy Jewels: If he can but corrupt this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, all the ſtreams will be fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, out of it will proceed the worſt of Evils; when it becomes the worſt part, which ſhould be the beſt.</p>
               <p>The Father of ſpirits doubles his Charge upon our ſpirits; The Lord God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaith, Take heed to your ſpirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.15, 16.</note> take heed to your ſpirit. Here the unclean ſpirits muſter up their Forces, and therefore here muſt our main Guard be; Watch but the heart ſo, as to keep him out there, and put the Devil out of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170191:89"/>heart, hee'l deſpair of you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Watch the good Spirit of God, in all its motions, impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, convictions, allurings, comfortings, &amp;c. as ever you would eſcape the temptations and deluſions of the evil ſpirit: and therefore,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Watch the good Spirit, to welcome him; make much of his ſweet breathings, ther's much life and love in them. If the Spirit come to Convince you, ſaying, (as <hi>Nathan</hi> did to <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Thou art the man;</hi> ſay, <hi>Speak Lord, for thy ſervant heareth.</hi> Be ready to hear of that ear, though he ſpeak ſuch things as make it tingle, as you love the peace of your own ſpirits. If he come as a Spirit of glory and power to ſubdue your iniquities, to cut off your right hand, &amp;c. with his two edged ſword: Oh ſay, Let him go on and proſper,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170191:89"/>till he have ſlain his thouſands, &amp;c: and made all his enemies become his footſtool; If he come to coaſt as a Dove upon you, to meeken and ſweeten your Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; Oh put forth your hands to take him in (as <hi>Noah</hi> did the Dove with the Olive-leafe); make both much of, and ſet much by the good Spirit and Word of God, and the evill Spirit will not be able to do you much hurt. Oh prize the gracious manudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of this faithfull guide at an high rate, and be as glad of his heavenly conduct, as the wiſe men were to ſee the ſtarre that pointed out Chriſt to them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 2.10.</note> they rejoyced with exceeding great joy; Lie as even as you can under his celeſtial influences, and ſweet diſtillings of the precious dews of grace and peace; At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his glorious miniſtration all along, let him have his whole
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170191:90"/>will upon you, and do his work wholly and fully within you, ſay him not Nay in any thing; &amp; he will work mightily within you, and witneſſe manifeſtly to you.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Watch the workings and witneſſings of the Holy Spirit, ſo as you may not hinder him, when he comes to help you, nor grieve him, when he comes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you, take heed of tempting him, who only can help you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Tempter, oh ſhut not out his glorious light for all the glory of the World; impriſon not any of his precious truths for all the ſpecious libertyes under the Sun; reſiſt not the ſtirring po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of his grace upon you, when hee's ſhaking the powers of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe within you; refuſe not the free and familiar tenders of his heart-renewing and reviving love, for thouſands of Gold and
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170191:90"/>Silver; Loſe not willingly one ſyllable of the ſecret whiſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of this meſſenger of peace, leſt he with draw his light, love, power, and peace, and leave you to the power of Satan, and he lead you into Priſon, and keep you in darkneſſe; Alas, alas, we have given the greateſt occaſion and advantage, to ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickedneſſe in high places to tempt, vex, diſturb and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide us; by tempting, vexing, and quenching the Holy Spirit; as ever any in the World have done; And; are not now the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the evening upon us, for ſlighting his goings forth as the morning? How ſtrangely have the lying Spirits deceived us; ſince the Spirit of truth has been rejected, and the truths of the Spirit? What a thick, black, dark hour of temptation is come upon us ſince we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170191:91"/>the cleare counſel and pure comforts of the Holy-Ghoſt, in the day of his gracious viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; what ſtrong deluſions and ſtrange declinings to the right hand or the left, ſince we have forſaken the guide of our ſpirits?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Watch your ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; they watch us,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.13.</note> as Satan did Chriſt; when the Tempter is gone, and his temptation, ſeemes to be quite over, he does but watch another ſeaſon, and therefore we muſt watch in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and out of ſeaſon; As <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah</hi> and the people of God with him, did with <hi>Sanballat</hi> and the enemies of God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.7.8.9.</note> they prayed and ſet a watch day and night; the enemie was very wroth, and they were very watchfull; a ſword in one hand, when at work with the other: So ſhould we at this day; watch at the Lords work; Watch and Pray,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170191:91"/>watch and heare, watch and ſpeak, &amp;c: 'Tis very ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that counſell of the mightie Counſellour? Take heed no man deceive you, for many ſhall come in my name, ſaying, I am Chriſt &amp; deceive many. Oh how much are we concerned in that bleſſed caution, upon whom the ends of the World are come?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.4, 5, 11, 24, 25.</note> How affectionate and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate was <hi>Paul</hi> the aged and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perienced, in warning the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple night and day, and that with teares to beware of ſuch as ſhould ſeeke to withdraw them from the Goſpel of Chriſt. Do not ſpiritual dangers multiply upon us every day, whiles we are under a Spirit of ſlumbring ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie from our ſoul-enemies, and that on every ſide; Oh what need of the whole Armour of God, on the right hand and on the left; what need of a diligent
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170191:92"/>ſpiritual watch, over our heads and hearts, words and wayes, teachings and hearings! Oh ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up your ſpiritual forces e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, and call in auxiliaries from Heaven, and follow the Captain of your ſalvation, Watching and Praying (as the armour-bearer did <hi>Jonathan</hi> climbing upon heads and feet) contend eameſtly for the faith which was once given to the Saints; and as you're fighting the good fight of faith, be ever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to Jeſus,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</note> and you ſhall be kept as in a Garriſon (ſo the word imports) by his power, through faith unto ſalvation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Watch over, and for one another, for good, in an evil time; 'tis very ſeaſonable to be knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at one anothers doores, and jogging at each others elbowes in the Spirit of meekneſſe, to keep as many awake as you can, in
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170191:92"/>this ſlumbring time, through the good hand of God upon you; and ſurely they, whoſe hearts are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakened in ſuch a day as this, by the Lords ſpeaking from heaven to them, cannot keep ſilence, but muſt be ſpeaking to their brethren in the name of the Lord ſaying, awake, awake; As our hearts ſhould dwell much upon awakening meditations, ſo our mouths ſhould be filled with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening ſalutations and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, when we meet with the ſervants of Chriſt (as it was with the lively Chriſtians in the primitive times) ſaying behold he comes like a thief; and, The Judge ſtandeth at the door, and the like: When ſo many watch one anothers haltings; let us watch to be helpers of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faith and joy, by provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another to Watching and Prayer; when many fellow-ſervants
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170191:93"/>are ſmiting one another with words of violence and veru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, let us ſmite one another with words of truth &amp; ſoberneſs; and the deeper they pierce the heart in the Spirit of Love, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter could we hit one another o'th heart-vein, 'twould be a mercy: Oh that the righteous would thus ſmite one another, with gracious words of reproof, to reſtore one another, and all in much mutual ſoul-love what a kindneſs would this be? Such precious oyntments would not break the head but mollifie and meeken the heart: Such wounds would be welcome from the hand of a friend. Alas, we complain every where of the Saints ſlumbring, wandring, and wantonneſſe; 'twere better we turned our complaints inward, and left them upon our ſelves, that we do not ſtir up one another to Watching and Prayer; we do but bear one another as bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170191:93"/>upon our ſpirits, when we ſhould beare one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, and help at a dead lift, as with one ſhoulder; we ſee poore Chriſtians in a dead ſleep on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very hand, and we lie dying by them, but who calls upon them, to be watchfull, and ſtrengthen the things that are readie to die?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.2.</note> How many have our eyes beheld lying as a man aſleep upon the top of a Maſt, and floods of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation under them too,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>prov.</hi> 7.23.34.</note> readie to ſwallow them up; but how few have we laboured to awaken to this day?<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17.</note> may we not reflect upon our ſelves in the words of <hi>Abſalom</hi> to <hi>Huſhai:</hi> Is this our kindneſſe to our friends? Is this nothing to you, all ye that paſſe by, do you not take notice how many fooliſh Virgins lie ſlum-bring and languiſhing upon beds of ſenſualitie and ſecuritie, and the houſe readie to be ſet on fire
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170191:94"/>over their heads; and do you take no care to awaken them; would it not pitty your very heart; to ſee the flames ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, while they are aſleep? How long has the keeper of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> watched over them, and kept them as the apple of his eye, notwithſtanding all their ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brings and wandrings; and does he not expect (think you) that you ſhould be your brethrens keeper for his ſake, and cry unto them in all haſte to prepare to meet him, leaſt he withdraw the wing of his protection from them, and leave them naked; if you ſee your brethren ſleeping, ſtarving, dying, and ſhut up the bowels of your compaſſions from them in ſuch a caſe, how dwels the love of God in you? And if you ſay, 'tis not in mans power to awaken anothers heart, who cannot awaken his own; can a
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170191:94"/>man raiſe the dead? Tis true, the low voyce of a weak man can never make thoſe hearts heare, which can ſleep under the loud thundrings of Heaven; why but can you weep over them, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> did over <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his grave? yea can feelingly ſigh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, ſaying, Can theſe drie bones live? Who ſhall roul a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſtone, and open their graves; why he that is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and the life, can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken them out of the deepeſt ſleep, and quicken them with a word of his mouth; If Jeſus will but groan in Spirit with you, and ſay, awake, ariſe, come forth, the dead ſhall heare his voyce and live. You cannot lift up their ſleepie hearts, no alas, they are too heavie for you; but cannot you lift up a prayer for them? If any man ſee his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſin a ſin not unto death, he
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170191:95"/>ſhall ask,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.16.</note> and he ſhall give him life; what high encouragement is here to praying-ſouls to lift up their voice on high, for ſuch as are ſinning and ſleeping in ſin al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to death; oh then if the Spirit of prayer were raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from the dead (as one may ſay) what bleſſed hopes would there be of a ſpiritual reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to many poor hearts, that are even dead and buried in the grave of ſecuritie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Secondly double your duty of Prayer; Pray, Pray.</head>
               <p n="1">1. For a plentifull and powerful effuſion of the Holy Spirit to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel &amp; comfort our fooliſh faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit in this hour of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Tis ſad to behold, ſince we have cauſed the good Spirit to withdraw his gracious influences how the glory is departed in a great meaſure from Churches,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170191:95"/>ordinances, communions, &amp;c: in moſt places; may we not ſadly ſigh out that heart-breaking word <hi>Ichabob,</hi> and ſay, Where is the glory; how many choyſe Gardens of the Saints are wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, ſince the Lord has with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the ſpiritual dewes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? How thin and lean is <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> become, and waxen pale, ſince a famine of the Spirit has been amongſt us? How ſpirit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, faithleſſe, heartleſſe, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, loveleſſe are moſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans grown, ſince we have ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred and ſinn'd away, the ſpirit of faith, life, love, power &amp;c: How is the Gold become dimme the fine Gold changed, now he that has the ſeven Spirits is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed aſide from the Golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks? Oh it is high time then, to begge as for life, that the Spirit would come down as floods upon the drie ground, that
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170191:96"/>the Churches may be as watred Gardens, and the Saints may grow up as willowes by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſes; oh let all the awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened Servants of Chriſt, cry as with one heart and mouth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.16.</note> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake O North-wind, and come thou South, blow upon the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, that the ſpices thereof may flow out; that our beloved may come into his Garden, and eate his pleaſant fruits; oh when, when ſhall a precious box of oyntments be broken over us, to fill our hearts with its ſavour? Oh when will the ſpirit come down amongſt us as a refiners fire or fullers ſope,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.3 4.</note> to purifie us as Gold and Silver, that we may offer up pure offerings of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, which may be pleaſant to the Lord, as in the dayes of old? Oh that we could wait in the Spirit (as old <hi>Simeon</hi> did for the conſolation of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) for that
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170191:96"/>power from on high, that ſo ſtrengthens weak hearts &amp; hands that the feeble may be as <hi>David;</hi> for ſuch an anointing with freſh oyle, as may cauſe us to move ſwiftly and ſweetly after Jeſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>And we have many precious cords of love let down to pull at, for this gracious Goſpel-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 14. &amp; 15 16</note> As the ſpecial promiſe of the Father of mercies to ſend the comforter, oft repeated for our better aſſurance; and he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that hath promiſed; he will not deny his people long, nor alwaies, for he cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelf. And the effectual prayer of our Lord Jeſus, who never prayes amiſſe, but is heard alwaies of his Father; This was that ſweeteſt myrrhe which dropt from the lips of Chriſt, as he was aſcending up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170191:97"/>his greateſt laſt Teſtament-promiſe of a double portion of his Spirit: Now, is it ſo much upon the Lords heart to beſtow this peculiar bleſſing, and ſhould it not be much upon our heart to aske it; eſpecially being that glorious miniſtration, which is to continue, for the ſupport, ſupply, and ſolace of the Saints, till the appearance of Jeſus Chriſt, without which no out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward adminiſtration can be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Oh Pray,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 2.6.8.</note> Pray, that <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah would ſet his King upon his holy hill of</hi> Zion, <hi>that the Heathen may be his inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the earth his poſseſſion:</hi> that <hi>the government may be upon his ſhoulder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.6.</note> 
                  <hi>who is clothed with a veſture dipt in blood,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.13.16.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and hath on his thigh a Name written, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords; that
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170191:97"/>all things may be opened and ſhut by the Key of David.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.11, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord is ariſing to ſhake terribly the Earth, the loftineſſe of man muſt be bowed down, and the haughtineſſe of men made low, that the Lord alone may be exalted in his day.</hi> Oh that the Sun of righteouſneſſe were at this height once, there would be a glorious Sun-ſhine day indeed. The God of heaven and earth has promiſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 12 26, 27, 28.</note> he will <hi>once more ſhake heaven and earth,</hi> to bring in that <hi>Kingdom that cannot be ſhaken, and the things that ſhall remain;</hi> and Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, rather then one tittle of his good promiſe ſhall fall to the ground. The Fathers heart is all upon his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, in whom his Soul delighteth, to <hi>exalt Him highly,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
                  <hi>give Him a Name above every Name.</hi> And ſhall not the hearts of his Children go in with him,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170191:98"/>and work ſtrongly that way? It was for their ſakes he humbled himſelf ſo low, even to <hi>the death of the Croſſe.</hi> Oh how ſhould their hearts break with longings, that he may be extolled, and be very high, crowned with maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and glory? Why then let all the Lords Remembrancers make mention of this good thing promiſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 33.14.</note> (of which he loves to be put in remembrance) before him night and day, that Jeſus Chriſt may take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf his great power and reign. On when ſhall the ſounding of the ſeventh Angel be heard, as the great voyces in Heaven, all the world over, ſaying; <hi>The Kingdoms of this world are become the Kingdomes of our Lord and of his Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and he ſhall reign for ever and ever.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.10.</note> Oh that King <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> would ſend his Chariot, that is paved with love, for the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170191:98"/>Sonnes and Daughters of <hi>Zion,</hi> that they may enter with joy and gladneſſe into the Kings Palace; how would their ſpirits revive within them? and they would ſay, It is enough.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Improve the Spirit of grace to the utmoſt; for the chaining up the unclean ſpirit. Oh try what power you have with the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> to ſet his power on work to ſhake the powers of darkneſſe. If Fervent Prayer, lift up by the hand of faith, bind Gods hand, and put him to ſay, Let me alone; will it not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, to bind up Satan, and to bruiſe him under the feet of his Saints ſhortly. The Devill is come down with great wrath, becauſe he knoweth he hath but a ſhort time. He followes his Kingdom with greateſt violence towards its period; hee's hot upon't, throwing with fury his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170191:99"/>fiery darts round about. The Adder's poyſon is boyling up to the height. This enemy is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon us like a flood: Oh 'tis high time to ſet upon the gates of Heaven with an humble and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly violence, knocking day and night, till the holy Spirit come down with prayer, and lift up a Standard againſt him.</p>
               <p>The old Serpent has now above 5000. years experience upon his back; hee's now maſter indeed of his black Art. Oh what multifariety and Variety in his methods? what Subtletie and ſecrecy in his ſnares? how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive and obſtructive are his devices and depths? Oh when will the Angel come down from Heaven with that great chain, and lay hold on the Dragon and bind him?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.1, 2, 3.</note> Ah, what a world of miſchief will he do, if he be let looſe awhile? For now this
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170191:99"/>Prince of darkneſſe transforms himſelf into an Angel of light, to bring in the greateſt dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and the Devil in white, or the white Devil, is moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deceitful; now, like the adulterer mentioned <hi>Job</hi> 24.15. he diſguiſeth himſelf, or ſets his face in ſecret, (ſo the Original) that he may beguile and defile us, and we never know it; and be moſt and beſt at his wicked work, when leaſt in ſight. He has put on a vizard of profeſſion, and now playes the thief in grain, ſtealing away the power and heart of pure Religion. He has oyl in his mouth, and truth in his tongue; but warre and a lie in his heart. And how many are betrayed with his flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering kiſſes, killed with his falſe kindneſſe, and by ſwallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down his ſugred, poyſonous pills greedily? How many are
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170191:100"/>taken with the fine hair of the Locuſts that aſcend out of the bottomleſſe pit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.8, 10,</note> who ſting them with their tailes as Scorpions. Oh then if ever you pitied poor ſilly ſoules, laden with ſin, and led Captive by Satan; now pity and pray for them much more: Oh cry out (as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trothed Damſel fearing raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to the Captain of your Salvation, to <hi>lead Captivity Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> to reſcue his darlings from the Lions, and to ſhorten this hour of temptation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Oh Pray, Pray, for a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpiritual reſurrection of the hearts and lives of the Saints, after ſo great a death has paſt upon them; that times of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing and reviving may come from the preſence of the Lord, to the decaying and deſponding Spirits of his people; Oh what a bleſſed, beautifull ſight,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170191:100"/>would ſuch an heavenly Spring bee,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 2.11.12. <hi>c.</hi> 7.12.13.</note> after this heart-withering winter ſeaſon? Would the flowers of the ſpouſes Garden flouriſh once, the Pome-granats bud forth, and the tender grape ſend forth a good ſmell: then would the ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of birds, and the voyce of the turtle be heard in our land, and we might chearfully, get up early to the Vineyards. Oh be earneſt with the Father of Spirits to ſend down a ſpeciall anointing from on high, for the new-ſpiriting of his people, for the work of their generation; A common Spirit will not carry them thorough ſpecial ſervice; no, it muſt be that other Spirit that <hi>Caleb</hi> had; or they'l never follow the Lord, fully; The Sonnes and Daughters of <hi>Zion</hi> muſt be awaked, to put on beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull garments, and ſhake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the duſt, as they
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170191:101"/>that are redeemed from the earth, and from men, as ever they would appeare in a good Goſpel-poſture to follow the Lamb, witherfoever he goeth; they muſt be putting on that <hi>new Man, which</hi> after God, <hi>is created in righteouſneſse and true holineſſe, and be renewed in the Spirit of their minds,</hi> or they'l have no heart, to think of the New Heaven and new Earth, wherein righteouſneſſe ſhall dwell. That work which the Lord is carrying on in the world, is high and heavenly, much above the world. A low-ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; earthly-minded Generation can never reach it, their poor flat ſpirits muſt needs ſhrink from it, or ſinck under it, at one time or other. Oh they had need of gracious, excellent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, changing from glory to glory, by the Spirit of glory
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170191:101"/>reſting on them; who looke to keep pace or hold any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, comfortable correſponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compliance, with thoſe glorious Works which the Lord will bring forth in the latter dayes, who is <hi>Wonderfull in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and excellent in Working.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Why then, 5. let us look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as one main work of the day, to ſet ſaith on work at the promiſes by prayer, for Judges as at the firſt, and Counſellours as at the beginning; men of choiſe ſpirits anſwerable to <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro's</hi> choyce: able men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 18.21.</note> fearing God, men of truth, hating cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe; And while I am ſtirring you up, to make ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to the Lord our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that he would graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vouch-ſafe, a peculiar unction and qualification, to ſuch as are in authoritie; let me ſet before your eyes, one of the firſt
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170191:102"/>and faireſt patterns, deſerving to be ſet in letters of Gold, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon our hearts, as with the point of a Diamond; the pureſt Primitive mould of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Juſtice, ſweetly meeting together in the righteous breaſt of <hi>Job,</hi> and ſtriving (as it were) for ſuper-eminency and victory: As <hi>for righteouſneſse; he clothed himſelf with it;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job.</hi> 29.11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and judgment was to him as a diadem; he brake the Jawes of the oppreſſors, and pluckt the ſpoile out of his teeth; and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the poor that cryed, and the Fatherleſse, and him that had none to help him.</hi> As for mercy, his condeſcention and compaſſion is very remarkable; when he ſate chief, and dwelt as a King in the Army; hee was as one that comforteth the mourners; <hi>A Father to the Poor and Fatherleſſe; eyes to the blind, and feet to the tame,</hi> who cauſed the heart of the
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170191:102"/>widdow to ſing, and the bleſſing of ſuch as were readie to periſh came upon him; Oh that Jeſus Chriſt, that bleſſed and only potentate, would make all our Governours and Magiſtrates willing in the day of his power, to kiſſe the Son, in humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection &amp; heartie affection to his righteous Scepter; and to lay down both ſword and Scepter at his feet (as the Elders did with their Crownes): Oh that there were in them ſuch an heart; as to ſay with the inhabitants of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> in their hearts? <hi>The inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Jeruſalem ſhall be our ſtrength, in the Lord of Hoſts their God.</hi> That they may be as <hi>nurſing Fathers to the</hi> Saints, the Children of the moſt high, yea the leaſt of Chriſts bretheren; accounting it their greateſt glory and praiſe, to promote the glory of the King immortal and eternal, the only
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170191:103"/>wiſe God; <hi>to be a praiſe to thoſe that doe well, and a terrour to evil doers,</hi> putting ſinners to ſhame: oh that the <hi>Rock of Iſrael</hi> that ſpake it, would make it good; That they that <hi>rule over men, muſt be juſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3.4,</note> 
                  <hi>ruling in the feare of God: And they ſhall be as the light of the morning, when the Sun ariſeth,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>a morning without Clouds, as the tender graſse ſpringing out of the earth, by cleare ſhining after rain.</hi> Why let us open our hearts and mouths wide (by the help of the Spirit) for ſuch a bleſſing, as thus waited for <hi>Job,</hi> even as for the latter rain.</p>
               <p>And ſpread thoſe good old pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes before the Lord, which are as freſh upon his heart as ever, to renew them in theſe latter daies; <hi>That Saviours ſhall come upon Mount-Zion, to judge the mount of Eſau, and the Kingdom ſhall be the
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170191:103"/>Lords;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Obad. v. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That he will raiſe up Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to break the horns, that ſcatter Judah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo that no man can lift up his head;</hi> That he will put that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour upon his Saints, <hi>To execute the Judgment that is written,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.6.9.</note> 
                  <hi>with a two-edged ſword in their hands, and the high praiſes of God in their mouthes. That the faithful choſen and true, clothed in fine and white linnen, ſhall give blood to drink,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev,</hi> 18.6.14.</note> 
                  <hi>to the woman, which is drunken with the blood of the Saints, and the Martyrs of Jeſus, and ſhall deſtroy that great City which reigneth over the Kings of the Earth; and ſhall overcome all his and their enemies in the blood of the Lamb; for he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings.</hi> Oh then let the prayers of all the Saints meet upon the golden Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3.4.</note> that the ſmoke of the incenſe may aſcend up before God day and night; and let them cry with a loud voyce, ſaying, <hi>How long,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170191:104"/>O Lord, holy and true,</hi> &amp;c?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Pray, pray, for the fulneſſe of the bleſſing of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt, upon all pure Evangelicall adminiſtrations;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13.16.</note> That Jeſus Chriſt would walk <hi>in the midſt of the golden Candleſticks;</hi> hold the ſtars in his right hand, that the golden pipes may empty the golden oyl out of themſelves from the Olive tree;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.11.12.</note> and his ſervants be anointed with the oyl of gladneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15.</note> who deſire to keep the Commandments of God, and the teſtimony of Jeſus. And that he would ſend Paſtours according to his own heart, that may feed the people with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding; able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Letter, but of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and ſend them forth in the power and ſpirit of <hi>Elijah,</hi> to turn many to the Lord.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.3, 4, 9.</note> And that the good Shepherd would
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170191:104"/>call his own ſheep by name, lead them out and go before them; that they may know his voyce, and follow him, and go in and out and find paſture.</p>
               <p>That his little flock receiving the Goſpel not in word onely, but alſo in power, and in the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.5.</note> and in much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; may have that glorious Character of the Church of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphia,</hi> as a Crown of twelve Stars upon their heads; that they have kept the Word of his patience, and have not denyed his Name;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.8.10.</note> who will keep them in this hour of Temptation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
